<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The grove, or, Love's paradice an opera, represented at the Theatre Royal in Drury-lane / by Mr. Oldmixon.</title>
            <author>Oldmixon, Mr. (John), 1673-1742.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53311</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O258</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6491</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12988428</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12988428</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96247</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53311)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96247)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 724:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The grove, or, Love's paradice an opera, represented at the Theatre Royal in Drury-lane / by Mr. Oldmixon.</title>
                  <author>Oldmixon, Mr. (John), 1673-1742.</author>
                  <author>Purcell, Daniel, 1660?-1717.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 46, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Parker ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Without the music, written by Daniel Purcell.</note>
                  <note>Libretto by: John Oldmixon.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96247:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96247:1"/>
            <p>THE GROVE, OR, Love's Paradice.</p>
            <p>AN OPERA, Repreſented at the Theatre Royal in <hi>Drury-lane.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>— Aut famam ſequere, aut Sibi Convenientia finge.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hor. Art. Poet.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>By Mr <hi>Oldmixon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Parker</hi> at the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn</hi> under the Piazza of the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:96247:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96247:2"/>
            <head>TO Mr. Freeman.</head>
            <p>AT laſt, SIR, Fortune has put it in my pow'r to pay you ſome acknowledgement for the many obligations you have laid on me; and I ſhall have the leſs reaſon to complain of her, if you receive this Preſent with as much pleaſure as I give it; of which I ſhou'd not deſpair, had I taken any other method in ſend ng it to you. But what might have been welcome from a Friend, will not, I fear, be ſo agreeable from an Author. Tho your inclination for the Drama, your acquaintance with the Art, and the incouragement you have given thoſe who devote them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to it, are ſufficient to warrant this Liberty in me, was I not otherwiſe ſecure in your Friendſhip. I can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver believe you will condemn in publick, what you ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove in private, and the Protection of one who knows how to defend what he thinks deſerves it, is certainly more valuable than the greateſt Name or the higheſt Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. I had rather have the world convinc'd, that their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to this Play is reaſonable, than by taking ſanctuary in the Degree or Intereſt of my Patron, forbid 'em the free uſe of their Underſtanding, and arbitrarily exact a Judgment from 'em, which in any other preſence they would recant or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own.</p>
            <p>The Poets have generally been careful not to Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate their Poems to thoſe who knew their true value: This would not at all have anſwer'd their deſign. They choſe out ſome perſons who wanted very thing more than Money, and they have ſeldom miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry'd in what they aim at moſt. Flattery is always ſold to theſe to the beſt advantage; and ſince it coſts 'em no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a few Pieces, which they cou'd not tell how better to diſpoſe of, the Trade has conſiderably advanc'd;
<pb facs="tcp:96247:3"/>
and thoſe who deal in't, have commonly found their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count by it. Fame is not the Miſtreſs they Court: To talk of a future Reputation when a preſent Supply is to be rais'd, wou'd to them ſeem Silly and Extravagant. Indeed I think they are very much to be excus'd; for a man muſt have little Stomach to hear of an Immortal Name, when his own puts him in mind of Mortality.</p>
            <p>This has fixt a ſcandal on theſe Addreſſes, but like other good things, they ought not to ſuffer becauſe they are abus'd; and while we are in a Humour of Reformation, 'twould be well if ſome amendment was begun in this too. That Authors wou'd make choice of Gentlemen, where they may be as liberal as they pleaſe of their Panegyrick, and yet preſerve their Sincerity. Perhaps 'tis difficult to find many ſuch Subjects, but that there are ſuch, you are yourſelf an undeniable inſtance. You have given us a fair proof, that Buſineſs, Letters, Pleaſure and Virtue, are not incompati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and that Wit, Judgment, and Good Manners, are not confin'd to the narrow limits of <hi>Convent Garden.</hi> If to be Idle is to be Uſeleſs, if Detraction is a Vice, Affectation Folly, and Pride a defect of the Soul, how many Wits and fine Gentlemen will at once loſe their Characters? You have on the contrary, preferr'd Care and Induſtry to Riot and Profuſion, tho you might with others have pleaded the excuſe of an ample Fortune. Your Wit does not ſupport itſelf by Satyr, nor your Judgment by Malice, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther does your good Humour loſe you any thing in the eſteem of all that know you; tho Spleen and ill Nature are grown ſo faſhionable, that in ſome places you will be thought ridiculous, if you are not troubleſom. But I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get this Epiſtle is to go farther than your own Family, and to bring you into others, who may not be ſo fond of this Theme as I am; for there is nothing ſo tedious to Mankind in general, as an Encomium, where they are not rhemſelves concern'd, let it be never ſo Juſt and Impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am, <hi>Sir, Your oblig'd humble Servant,</hi> J. Oldmixon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:96247:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Never knew a Book get much by a Preface, nor a Play by this means advance in the Opinion of the world, unleſs it had triumph'd on the Stage. I think, however, we ought to acknowledge the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of ſuch as have us'd us well, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the reſt; 'tis poſſible they may be miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</p>
            <p>As far as this is my caſe, I believe the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd a Man was accountable for no failings but his own, and if there was any thing amiſs which was not the Author's, they were ſo juſt, as to diſtinguiſh between that part of the Drama which belong'd to him, and that which depended on others. As for the Perſons who were not ſo generous as theſe, nor in any reſpect ſo conſiderable, who thought the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrophe was not enough prepar'd, and that the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery in the laſt Act was huddled and in confuſion, they will now ſee if what he had writ had been ſpoken, every thing wou'd have appear'd clear and natural, which, to ſhorten the Entertainment, had been before broken and diſorder'd.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:96247:4"/>I might in the next place acquaint the Criticks, that this Play is neither Tranſlation nor Paraphraſe; that the Story is entirely now; that 'twas at firſt intended for a Paſtoral, tho in the three laſt Acts, the Dignity of the Characters rais'd it into the form of a Tragedy, and with theſe reflections inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, as is uſual, many things to my advantage.</p>
            <p>But men are heard with impatience in their own Cauſe, and I ſhall prevail more by the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Candour of the Reader, than a vain ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of my own performance.</p>
            <p>As to what relates to the compoſition, no man ever conſulted the meaning of Words more than Mr <hi>Parcel</hi> has done, and he has ſucceeded too well with the Publick, to want the applauſe of his Author.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:96247:4"/>
            <head>Dramatis Perſonae.</head>
            <list>
               <item>MEN.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>ARcadius,</hi> Emperor of <hi>Greece,</hi> Mr <hi>Mills.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Eudoſius,</hi> Prince of <hi>Thrace,</hi> living in <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> diſguis'd under the name of <hi>Amintor,</hi> Mr <hi>Powel.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> his Brother, Mr <hi>Tomms.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Parmenio,</hi> the Emperor's Favourite, Mr <hi>Cibber.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Nicias,</hi> Captain of his Guards, Mr <hi>Thomas.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Alcander,</hi> Servant to <hi>Eudoſius,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sileno,</hi> a Shepherd.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>WOMEN.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Aurelia,</hi> Daughter to the Emperor, Mrs <hi>Rogers.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Phylante,</hi> her Confident, Mrs <hi>Temple.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sylvia,</hi> a <hi>Roman</hi> Lady, Mrs <hi>Oldfield.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Officers, Guards, Shepherds and Shepherdeſſes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>SCENE.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A Province of</hi> Italy, <hi>near the Gulph of</hi> Venice.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:96247:5"/>
            <head>PROLOGUE.</head>
            <l>PLays would no more without a Prologue paſs,</l>
            <l>Than City Dinner wou'd without a Grace;</l>
            <l>Like theirs too ſome have been ſo long and dull,</l>
            <l>Before you taſte, your Stomachs have been full.</l>
            <l>Our Author's, to engage you for his treat,</l>
            <l>Like hungry Chaplains, ſhall be ſhort and ſweet.</l>
            <l>The Wits, he knows, are eaſy in their fare,</l>
            <l>They make the Stage their pleaſure, not their care</l>
            <l>The Criticks only like Informers ſit,</l>
            <l>To witneſs if we paſs unlawful Wit.</l>
            <l>Beſides, the Poets have this hardſhip in't,</l>
            <l>Each tries the Metal by his private Mint.</l>
            <l>They talk of Rules, and thoſe that break 'em ſcorn,</l>
            <l>Yet none more forward when it ſerves their turn.</l>
            <l>Good Senſe and Nature ev'ry where ſhould reign,</l>
            <l>Where theſe are wanting they but talk in vain.</l>
            <l>The precepts of their Art with heat they praiſe,</l>
            <l>But draw the vile examples from their Plays.</l>
            <l>Hard fate! if we muſt all their paths purſue,</l>
            <l>Or win their favour by offending you:</l>
            <l>To you bright Circle he commends his Cauſe,</l>
            <l>They muſt to him, who to the world give Laws.</l>
            <l>If Foreign Theatres, with mighty coſt,</l>
            <l>Of wondrous Scenes and Decorations boaſt;</l>
            <l>Of opening Heav'ns, and Viſions in the air,</l>
            <l>They ne're cou'd ſhew ſo many wonders there.</l>
            <l>Nor by the help of Magick or Machine,</l>
            <l>Produce ſuch Beauties, or ſo fair a Scene.</l>
            <l>Tho awful terrour in your eyes appears,</l>
            <l>He leſs your Cruelty than Juſtice fears.</l>
            <l>Yet by your ſentence ſince he lives or dies,</l>
            <l>He'll fall with Pleaſure, or with Glory riſe.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="act">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96247:5"/>
            <head>ACT I.</head>
            <stage>Scene an open Valley, whoſe Proſpect is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd by a Mountain on one ſide, and Woods on the other, and the Sea at a diſtance for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</stage>
            <stage>Aurelia, Sylvia, Phylante <hi>walking.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>WAk'd by the early Mattins of the Lark</l>
               <l>We leave our Down, and in this Sunny Vale</l>
               <l>Suck the freſh breezes which embalm the air.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sylv.</speaker>
               <l>Thus in the tedious abſence of your Lord,</l>
               <l>We by variety of Sports contrive</l>
               <l>To paſs thoſe hateful minutes with delight,</l>
               <l>Which elſe would lag like years of want and pain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Oh! 'tis an age, 'tis ages ſince my eyes</l>
               <l>Fed laſt on his, and to my Soul convey'd</l>
               <l>Unutterable pleaſure.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
               <l>Scarce the Sun</l>
               <l>Has thrice in yonder Ocean ſunk his beams</l>
               <l>Since you beheld him, and may yet e're noon</l>
               <l>Again behold, and have him in your arms.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phyl.</speaker>
               <l>See there—deſcending from the hill I ſpy</l>
               <l>A man, that tow'rds you ſeems to bend his courſe,</l>
               <l>So ſwiftly now he croſſes o're the Plain,</l>
               <l>'Tis ſure the Meſſenger of welcome news.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Oh! nothing can be welcome but my Lord.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phyl.</speaker>
               <l>I ſee him, 'tis <hi>Alcander.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Ha! alone.</l>
               <l>Where's my <hi>Amintor?</hi> Tell me, <hi>Phylante,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Has not <hi>Arcadius</hi> loaded him with Chains,</l>
               <l>And ſentenc'd him to Torture and to Death?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sylv.</speaker>
               <l>For what are you thus anxious of his Life?</l>
               <l>How wild are all theſe fears.</l>
               <l>You from <hi>Amintor</hi>'s merit may expect</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arcadius</hi> has been laviſh of his Grace,</l>
               <l>And with Imperial honors crown'd your Love.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:96247:6"/>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis not for us to think of Honors here,</l>
               <l>For what we never ſee, we ne're deſire.</l>
               <l>My Soul, contented with our humble ſtate,</l>
               <l>Leaves to the Great the glories of a Court;</l>
               <l>And in poſſeſſion of theſe Shades and Love,</l>
               <l>Unenvy'ng and unenvy'd, taſte delights,</l>
               <l>Which for <hi>Elizium</hi> I wou'd ſcarce reſign.</l>
               <l>But oh! If I, amidſt of all this joy,</l>
               <l>Shou'd have <hi>Amintor</hi> raviſht from my arms,</l>
               <l>And ſee him periſh by unnatural rage;</l>
               <l>This Vale will then be worſe than <hi>Libian</hi> Wilds,</l>
               <l>All will be deſert here, and all accurſt,</l>
               <l>Forſook by ev'ry thing but by deſpair</l>
               <l>I then ſhall wander in a maze of woe,</l>
               <l>Till death too late o'retakes me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sylv.</speaker>
               <l>What can this mean? This unexpected change,</l>
               <l>Gives me juſt reaſon to believe you've fears,</l>
               <l>Which you in vain endeavour to conceal;</l>
               <l>For I will know 'em, I that am your Friend,</l>
               <l>A name which claims the priviledge of truſt,</l>
               <l>Will know your worſt of Fate, as I till now</l>
               <l>Have been the partner of your hours of bliſs.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Alcander.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
               <l>Madam, my Lord.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Speak. Lives he? Is he free?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
               <l>He Lives, is free, and o're this Realm of Peace,</l>
               <l>Created by the Emp'ror, Soveraign Prince,</l>
               <l>As this informs you further.
<stage>Giving a Letter.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Yes 'tis his.</l>
               <l>Look in my eyes, and you'll perceive 'tis his.</l>
               <l>Why do I tremble? Is it fear or joy?</l>
               <l>Whom ſhou'd I fear? There's nothing ſure in this:</l>
               <l>There's nothing which my Lord can ſend to me,</l>
               <l>But what is dear as Life, and ſoft as Love.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Reads.</hi> Impatient of thy abſence, I commit</l>
               <l>In thee, the Treaſure of my heart to Heav'n.</l>
               <l>Our Embaſſy with rapture was receiv'd:</l>
               <l>Our Flocks and Herds, the ric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es of the Plain,</l>
               <l>Preferr'd to heaps of Gold, and homage Crowns.</l>
               <l>I am declar'd a Prince, and thou ſhalt reign</l>
               <l>If we ſurvive the danger of this day.</l>
               <l>The Emp'ror from our Foes or Fame has heard</l>
               <l>So much of our bleſt Manſion, and of thee,</l>
               <l>He begg d to be my Gueſt, and with his Court,</l>
               <l>Intends to viſit our retreat e're even.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96247:6"/>I fly to thy relief, I can — no more.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sylv.</speaker>
               <l>Why weep you, when your fortune is advanc'd</l>
               <l>Above what you expected or deſir'd,</l>
               <l>The Empire of our hearts you had before,</l>
               <l>But what was Friendſhip then is duty now,</l>
               <l>Nor ſhall our Friendſhip make our duty leſs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arcadius.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sylv.</speaker>
               <l>What of him? I know you think</l>
               <l>This place not worthy of the Lord of <hi>Greece,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Tho tis not for magnificence or ſhew,</l>
               <l>Or to ſee ſplendours equal with his own,</l>
               <l>That he deſcends to be your gueſt,</l>
               <l>'Tis to behold the ſweetneſs of this Vale,</l>
               <l>To hear the Muſick of our Foreſt Quires,</l>
               <l>And weary d with perpetual Pomp, to ſee</l>
               <l>How Solitude and Innocence can charm,</l>
               <l>For you perhaps, this journey is deſign'd.</l>
               <l>Your Beauty —</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Hold — I muſt not hear thee on,</l>
               <l>Thou little know'ſt of whom, or what thou talk'ſt:</l>
               <l>Ungratefully thy Friendſhip I've abus'd,</l>
               <l>And kept the myſtery of my fate conceal'd,</l>
               <l>Which now alas, neceſſity reveals.</l>
               <l>Come, gentle <hi>Sylvia,</hi> take me to thy heart,</l>
               <l>Support me with thy Counſel, leſt I ſink</l>
               <l>Beneath the burthen of my ſhame and fears:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arcadius</hi> Is my Father</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sylv.</speaker>
               <l>When you firſt came a ſtranger to theſe Woods,</l>
               <l>I ever thought you of divine deſcent,</l>
               <l>And as I thought you then adore you now.
<stage>kneels.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Oh riſe my Friend, I will not ſee thee thus.</l>
               <l>Say—does the Sun that glids this morning Sky</l>
               <l>Shine on a Creature ſo forlorn as me,</l>
               <l>Who can defend me from a Fathers frown,</l>
               <l>A Father and an Emperor diſobey'd?</l>
               <l>Forgive me, that I dare not tell thee more,</l>
               <l>Thou ſoon wilt gueſs, that Love was all my Crime.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sylv.</speaker>
               <l>And Love, which was your crime is your defence.</l>
               <l>Your ſtory at your leiſure I ſhall know.</l>
               <l>But 'tis no more than I have often read</l>
               <l>Of Princeſſes, who ſcorn'd the Beds of Kings,</l>
               <l>When merit had before engag'd their hearts.</l>
               <l>Your Father by his favour has approv'd</l>
               <l>The choice you made, and all things will be well.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:96247:7"/>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alcander</hi> execute your Lords commands.</l>
               <l>You <hi>Sylvia</hi> ſee that all things be prepar'd</l>
               <l>Fit to receive the Maſter of the World,</l>
               <l>While I with Reaſon and with Love conſult</l>
               <l>How beſt I may approach my Fathers wrath,</l>
               <l>How move his pity beſt, or daunt his rage.
<stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Syl. Alc.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Oh my <hi>Phylante,</hi> how ſhall we eſcape</l>
               <l>This Dreadful enterview, or rather meet</l>
               <l>The Storm which threatens to o'rewhelm us both.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <l>You've little cauſe to fear, for you are bleſt</l>
               <l>In the fruition of your wiſhes, I</l>
               <l>Have much more reaſon to deplore my fate,</l>
               <l>An Exile from my Parents and my hopes,</l>
               <l>Yet in your Friendſhip I enjoy 'em all.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Oh how cou'd we foreſee that we ſhou'd here,</l>
               <l>In this vile corner of the World, where none</l>
               <l>Scarce hear of <hi>Greece</hi> or of my Fathers name,</l>
               <l>How cou'd we think that here we ſhou'd have met</l>
               <l>The ruin, which we ſtrove ſo much to ſhun?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <l>Heaven always will protect the Innocent.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Who can be Innocent that diſobeys</l>
               <l>A Fathers pleaſure, and a Soveraign's Will?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <l>Your Father wou'd have left you to your choice,</l>
               <l>The Empreſs forc'd him to oppoſe your Vows,</l>
               <l>And in her Brothers favour wrong your Love.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Wrong'd it indeed, for from our Infant years</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Amintor</hi> ſtill was promis'd to my Arms</l>
               <l>But when <hi>Pulcheria</hi> dy'd was nam'd no more</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phyl.</speaker>
               <l>You were deſign'd the Prince of <hi>Thrace</hi>'s Bride.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>And who's <hi>Amintor,</hi> but the Prince of <hi>Thrace.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Adraſtus</hi> who poſſeſſes now his realm,</l>
               <l>Whom thou and every one, that knows him loves,</l>
               <l>Was Privy to our flight, and the deſign</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eudoſius</hi> form'd to ſave me for himſelf.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phyl.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis ſaid that Prince was in <hi>Arabia</hi> ſlain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>'Twas ſaid ſo then, the better to conceal</l>
               <l>The Plot <hi>Adraſtus</hi> had in <hi>Greece</hi> contriv'd,</l>
               <l>When he in Royal Embaſſy was ſent</l>
               <l>To fetch me for his Brother, as before</l>
               <l>The Emperor and <hi>Eudoſius</hi> had agreed.</l>
               <l>But all thoſe Treaties with my Mother dy'd,</l>
               <l>And the new Empreſs a new Match reſolv'd.</l>
               <l>How on this news <hi>Eudoſius</hi> was enrag'd,</l>
               <l>How from his Court diſguis'd he came to ours,</l>
               <l>What means he us'd to ſee me, and how ſoon</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96247:7"/>My Soul conſented to be rul'd by him.</l>
               <l>I only for his Fame ador'd before;</l>
               <l>This for ſome hour of leiſure I reſerve,</l>
               <l>The reſt is known to thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <l>I lik't implicitely the man you lov'd.</l>
               <l>Nor askt with whom we fled, but always thought</l>
               <l>His actions ſhew'd him of the race of Kings.</l>
               <l>Who now can ſay that Love forgets his Slaves?</l>
               <l>Love that has led you thro ſuch vaſt deſigns;</l>
               <l>And when the world to find their Princeſs roſe,</l>
               <l>That kept you from the ſearch of Nations free,</l>
               <l>That watch'd you on the Waves, and to this ſhoar</l>
               <l>Of ſafety guided you, and bleſt your flight.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Love on his part has every thing perform'd,</l>
               <l>But what have I, <hi>Phylante!</hi> done on mine,</l>
               <l>Rebellious and a Fugitive, can I</l>
               <l>Look on my Father and not ſink with ſhame?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <l>For what? He bid you love, and you obey'd.</l>
               <l>'Tis true, he bid you after this to change,</l>
               <l>But that was neither in his pow'r nor yours;</l>
               <l>You fled. From whom? <hi>Placidia,</hi> one who ſought</l>
               <l>Your ruine, and can hurt you now no more.</l>
               <l>Her pride and ſpite are bury'd in her Grave;</l>
               <l>The Emp'ror will behold you as his Child,</l>
               <l>And free'd from prejudice you'll then appear</l>
               <l>A Heavenly Treaſure, which he once had loſt,</l>
               <l>And now with rapture and amazement finds.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Thy words are extaſy, thy very looks</l>
               <l>Declare thy Prophecy Divine;</l>
               <l>And I already feel my tranſports grow,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arcadius</hi> will forgive me, I no more</l>
               <l>Shall claſp <hi>Eudoſius</hi> with reluctant arms.</l>
               <l>For when my heart with tenderneſs diſſolv'd,</l>
               <l>Has giv'n itſelf to pleaſure, ſay ye Groves,</l>
               <l>Ye Fountain, Hill and Dale, that know my Griefs,</l>
               <l>Has not my diſobedience checkt my joy,
<stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Sylvia.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>And drawn, when we've for ſolitude retir'd,</l>
               <l>A thouſand racking queſtions from my Lord,</l>
               <l>Which he no more ſhall ask, nor I provoke?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sylv.</speaker>
               <l>Reaſon prevails and you're your ſelf again,</l>
               <l>And this prophetick Peace declares you ſafe?</l>
               <l>You in the Grove of pleaſure, there are met</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sileno, Daphne,</hi> and the Nymphs whoſe ſports</l>
               <l>Are us'd to entertain your hour of mirth,</l>
               <l>Who waiting your approach, prepare their Songs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:96247:8"/>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>This ſure's no hour of Mirth, no time for ſports</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Sylvia,</hi> I'll indeavour to be calm,</l>
               <l>I'll ſet the faireſt proſpect to my View,</l>
               <l>And ſooth my hopes with Viſions of ſucceſs.</l>
               <l>Come, my <hi>Phylante,</hi> ſince from every Grove</l>
               <l>The cheerful Birds ſalute us with their Songs,</l>
               <l>Joyn thou thy better harmony with theirs,</l>
               <l>And lay the riſing Tempeſt in my Soul;</l>
               <l>Thy Voice is ſtill the refuge of my care,</l>
               <l>Deſpair herſelf would liſten to the Charm,</l>
               <l>And when thou entertainſt her loſe her ſting:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thrace,</hi> by the Magick of thy notes has heard</l>
               <l>More wonders, than her ancient fables boaſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="song">
                        <head>SONG.</head>
                        <lg n="1">
                           <head>I.</head>
                           <l>IN Vain you tell me Love is ſweet,</l>
                           <l>And boaſt of his delights,</l>
                           <l>I hear you talk of nothing yet,</l>
                           <l>But reſtleſs days and nights,</l>
                           <l>For when you have your wiſh enjoy'd,</l>
                           <l>You find the bliſs ſo ſmall,</l>
                           <l>You either think your Lover cloy'd,</l>
                           <l>Or that you han't him all.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="2">
                           <head>II.</head>
                           <l>Strange Magick when we ſee before</l>
                           <l>So many Fools undone</l>
                           <l>We long to make the number more,</l>
                           <l>And on their Perils run.</l>
                           <l>Tho thouſands ſhou'd our hopes reprove,</l>
                           <l>Who have their falſhood known,</l>
                           <l>In this we'll truſt, ſo weak is Love,</l>
                           <l>No knowledge but our own.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>The <hi>Thracian</hi> Prince may make the Fable true,</l>
               <l>And what you mean of others you may feel.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <l>Young <hi>Daphne</hi> and <hi>Sileno,</hi> and the Youth</l>
               <l>Who to divert you, form a rural Quire</l>
               <l>With their diviner Lays, ſhall cure you griefs,</l>
               <l>And health to your diſtemper'd mind reſtore.</l>
               <l>You then whoſe Angel voices and whoſe looks</l>
               <l>To raviſh every ſenſe,</l>
               <l>In heavenly conſort join</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96247:8"/>Attend!</l>
               <l>And what I taught you for your Lords return,</l>
               <l>To pleaſure his belov'd and yours perform.</l>
            </sp>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="scene">
                        <stage>The Front Scene opens and diſcovers a Circle of Seven Pillars adorn'd with Garlands of Flowers. The Shepherds and Shepherdeſſes dancing witkin it, to the Tune of the Chorus, which they ſing as they Dance.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                           <l>Come all away,</l>
                           <l>Come and Sing and Dance and Play</l>
                           <l>'Tis the Shepherds holiday.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>1 Shepherd.</speaker>
                           <l>Leave the Mountain, Vale, and Home,</l>
                           <l>To the Grove of Pleaſure come:</l>
                           <l>Never fear your Flocks will ſtray,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Pan</hi> protects 'em while we play.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Shepherdeſs.</speaker>
                           <l>Happy Manſions, pleaſant Shades,</l>
                           <l>Seats of Innocence and Eaſe;</l>
                           <l>Gentle Shepherds, Tender Maids,</l>
                           <l>Sweet Abodes of Smiling Peace,</l>
                           <l>Ev'ry Grace and Joy poſſeſſing,</l>
                           <l>Welcome him that gives the Bleſſing.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Shepherds</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Amintor</hi>'s Watchful Care maintains</l>
                           <l>Theſe Quiet Fields from harms,</l>
                           <l>His wiſdom awes the rougher Swains,</l>
                           <l>The Mild his Goodneſs charms.</l>
                           <l>When <hi>Pan</hi> the <hi>Grecian</hi> Shepherds ſway'd</l>
                           <l>He ne're was more ador'd,</l>
                           <l>They out of Fear their God obey'd,</l>
                           <l>We out of Love, our Lord.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Shepherdeſs.</speaker>
                           <l>When <hi>Venus,</hi> deckt with Heavenly Charms,</l>
                           <l>Once woo'd a Mortal to her Arms,</l>
                           <l>All but the cruel ſtupid Boy</l>
                           <l>Beheld her with tranſporting Joy;</l>
                           <l>The Flocks and Herds refus'd to graze,</l>
                           <l>And Men and Beaſts cou'd only gaze.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Aurelia</hi>'s Beauties thus appear,</l>
                           <l>Thus ſhining, thus tranſporting here.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Shepherd.</speaker>
                           <l>For him we Flowry Chaplets bring,</l>
                           <l>The faireſt praduct of the Spring.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96247:9"/>
                           <speaker>Shepherdeſs.</speaker>
                           <l>For her we Crowns of Roſes weave,</l>
                           <l>Which both with cheerful Looks receive,</l>
                           <l>And with as cheerful Hearts we g've,</l>
                           <l>Thus Loving and Belov'd we live.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                           <l>Thus Loving and Belov'd we Live.</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Oh force of Muſick and Caeleſtial Song,</l>
               <l>Which from profoundeſt miſery can raiſe</l>
               <l>A Soul to extaſy, and taſt of Heav'n</l>
               <l>To you <hi>Phylante!</hi> I commit the charge</l>
               <l>Of this great Feſtival, and from your care</l>
               <l>Expect what nature, and what art can do.
<stage>A March afar off.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>The foremoſt of the <hi>Graecian</hi> Court arrive,</l>
               <l>I ſee the Glorious Troop deſcend the Mount,</l>
               <l>And love informs me, that my Lord is there,</l>
               <l>To him I'll fly, and know what fate decrees;</l>
               <l>From him the ſharpeſt Meſſage will be ſweet,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Voice is kinder to my Ear than ſighs</l>
               <l>Of wandring Rivers, or of evening Winds.
<stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Aur. Syl.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phyl.</speaker>
               <l>Unhappy Princeſs! by ill fate perſu'd</l>
               <l>To theſe almoſt the limits of the World,</l>
               <l>Oh fatal paſſion! Thus while I lament</l>
               <l>Thy loſt condition, I forget my own,</l>
               <l>And Friendſhip always is too ſtrong for Love,</l>
               <l>For now that every hour I hope to ſee</l>
               <l>What next to thee is deareſt to my heart,</l>
               <l>Thy danger ſets before my eyes a gloom,</l>
               <l>Which hides the gawdy Viſion from my view,</l>
               <l>And makes it doubtful to me, if I ought</l>
               <l>To mourn for thee, or to rejoice for him.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sileno</hi> meet me at the Bow'rs of bliſs,</l>
               <l>There all ſhall have the Parts to each aſſign'd,</l>
               <l>What beſt my thoughts can thus employ'd invent;</l>
               <l>For ſomething noble we muſt now prepare,</l>
               <l>Something te raviſh an Imperial Ear,</l>
               <l>Tho from you only I expect ſucceſs,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Beauties equal with your Voices pleaſe.
<stage>Ex. omnes.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="act">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96247:9"/>
            <head>ACT II.</head>
            <stage>Scene a Fountain with Bowers of Myrtle around it, a Shepherdeſs lying in one that fronts the Stage ſings.</stage>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="song">
                        <head>SONG.</head>
                        <l>TO Hill and Dale I tell my Care,</l>
                        <l>To Rocks and Streams how I deſpair;</l>
                        <l>To faithleſs Winds my fortune mourn,</l>
                        <l>The Winds in ſighs my plaint return;</l>
                        <l>The Streams in murmurs, Hill and Dale,</l>
                        <l>And hollow Rocks my fate bewail</l>
                        <l>In Ecchoes kindly they reſound</l>
                        <l>My moan, and ſeem to feel my wound:</l>
                        <l>He only that ſhould hear is deaf,</l>
                        <l>He only that can give relief,</l>
                        <l>Deſpiſes me, and mocks my grief.</l>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <stage>Phylante, Sileno, <hi>Shepherds and Shepherdeſſes come to her as the Song begins.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phyl.</speaker>
               <l>What hapleſs Virgin haunts theſe lonely Bow'rs,</l>
               <l>Who with theſe mournful ſighs diſturbs our Plays?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Myrtilla?</hi> then 'tis but affected grief,</l>
               <l>Such beauty ne'r had reaſon to deſpair.</l>
               <l>Come, you to other notes muſt tune your voice,</l>
               <l>To ſing of Gods, and win immortal praiſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sileno,</hi> ſince you challenge us to try</l>
               <l>Whoſe Layes have greater influence on the Soul,</l>
               <l>Whether the Trumpets lofty ſounds prevail,</l>
               <l>Leſs than the dying whiſpers of your Flutes.</l>
               <l>Exert your utmoſt skill, for we accept</l>
               <l>Your offer, and your Valley ſhall reſound</l>
               <l>With Muſick, ſuch as Eccho ne'r can learn.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sileno.</speaker>
               <l>We boaſt no skill, but from our artleſs Songs</l>
               <l>Expect ſucceſs, which Nature never fails.</l>
               <l>When Birds untaught in Woods and Foreſts ſing,</l>
               <l>Their notes ſeem wild, and not ſo juſt as ours,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:96247:10"/>There's ſomething in 'em yet which charms our ears</l>
               <l>More than the fineſt graces of your art:</l>
               <l>Why mayn't our Voices, uninflam'd like theirs,</l>
               <l>Give the ſame Pleaſure, tho they ſeem as wild.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Amintor (<hi>or</hi> Eudoſius) <hi>and</hi> Aurelia.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phyl.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Amintor</hi> and <hi>Aurelia!</hi> Let's retire,</l>
               <l>And in the thickeſt of this beauteous ſhade</l>
               <l>Attend their leiſure to approve our mirth,</l>
               <l>There meditate the buſineſs of the day,</l>
               <l>And the rewards which we expect from Fame.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>I have thee, my <hi>Eudoſius,</hi> I have all</l>
               <l>That Heav'n can give me of my hearts deſire:</l>
               <l>I have thee, but how long ſhall I enjoy</l>
               <l>The mighty bleſſing? this is all my fear,</l>
               <l>And this the ſource of theſe untimely tears.</l>
               <l>My Father—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis not in the power of Man</l>
               <l>Nor Gods to part what Love ſo firmly joyns;</l>
               <l>Nor have we liv'd for many rolling years</l>
               <l>In ſweet fruition of our wiſh, and paſt</l>
               <l>Thro dangers eminent on both the Mains,</l>
               <l>To fall at laſt by him that gave thee life.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>He'll look on me perhrps as on a Child,</l>
               <l>The pangs of Nature may oppoſe his rage,</l>
               <l>I in the combat of his ſoul be ſafe,</l>
               <l>But how will you eſcape his dire revenge.</l>
               <l>He'll view thee as the robber of his houſe,</l>
               <l>That ſtole his deareſt treaſure thence, and lives</l>
               <l>Unlicens'd in poſſeſſion of thoſe joys,</l>
               <l>Which he and only he had right to give.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>That right by ſolemn Oaths he gave to me,</l>
               <l>Himſelf firſt tempted me to ſoar ſo high,</l>
               <l>To gaze upon thy Beauties with deſire,</l>
               <l>And when he wou'd have flung me from the Heav'n</l>
               <l>To which his promiſe had advanc'd my hopes,</l>
               <l>Oh was it poſſible for me to leave</l>
               <l>Such Sweetneſs, ſuch Divinity as thine:</l>
               <l>And yield thee to the boſom of thy Foe?</l>
               <l>What Danger cou'd have driven me to this,</l>
               <l>For whom had I to pleaſe but thee?</l>
               <l>Oh! were his power omnipotent as <hi>Jove</hi>'s,</l>
               <l>His will as ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ed, and his wrath as fierce,</l>
               <l>And I be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>d hee thus profuſely kind,</l>
               <l>What fear cou'd interdict me thy embrace?</l>
               <l>What duty check <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>y tranſport, or defend</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96247:10"/>My arms, this circle of inceſſant joy?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>To have thee thus, <hi>Eudoſius,</hi> tho I ſaw</l>
               <l>My Father darting from his awful brow</l>
               <l>His keeneſt arrows, yet my ſoul ſecure</l>
               <l>In extaſy, wou'd brave 'em all for thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>Away with ſorrow, Fate already ſhews</l>
               <l>A boundleſs ſtore of happineſs reſerv'd</l>
               <l>To recompence the troubles we have paſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>What made <hi>Arcadius</hi> viſit our retreat?</l>
               <l>What made this ſhow'r of favour fall on thee?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>When, choſen by theſe Provinces, I went</l>
               <l>To pay the homage which our Lord requires,</l>
               <l>Our Preſents, Flocks and Herds, and crowns of Flow'rs,</l>
               <l>Were to the wealth of <hi>Italy</hi> preferr'd.</l>
               <l>He askt me, whence this plenty, and theſe Youth?</l>
               <l>Who rul'd for him, the Region whence they came?</l>
               <l>And raviſht with their Elegance and Looks,</l>
               <l>Declar'd this morn <hi>Amintor</hi> for their Lord,</l>
               <l>As they with tears of earneſtneſs implor'd.</l>
               <l>Of you, Sir, ſmiling from the Throne on me,</l>
               <l>He ſaid, we've heard ſuch wonders, we reſolve</l>
               <l>To ſee the Paradice which you poſſeſs,</l>
               <l>And be our ſelf a witneſs of your ſports.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Adraſtus</hi>— what of him?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>My care of thee</l>
               <l>Prevented me from being further known:</l>
               <l>For tho I dy'd to take him to my heart,</l>
               <l>I durſt not let our Friendſhip then appear,</l>
               <l>Leſt e're we were prepar'd to meet his frown,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arcadius</hi> had been jealous of our loves,</l>
               <l>And we unheard had faln before his wrath,</l>
               <l>Which now we may defeat, or elſe avoid.
<stage>Trumpets are heard.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Hark, others of the Royal Train arrive,</l>
               <l>The Trumpet ecchoes in this Vale of Peace,</l>
               <l>A noiſe more dreadful than the din of War.
<stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Edraſtus.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>Sink on my breaſt, and loſe thy terrors there.</l>
               <l>Oh, my <hi>Aurelia!</hi> if thou yet haſt life,</l>
               <l>Look on a ſight which will enchant thy Soul.</l>
               <l>My Brother! why doſt thou behold me thus?</l>
               <l>Why cruelly detain thee from my arms?</l>
               <l>What meſſage haſt thou brought, are we proſcrib'd?</l>
               <l>Is Death preſented us by thee, my friend?</l>
               <l>I cannot argue with thee, nor endure</l>
               <l>This diſtance. Oh <hi>Adraſtus!</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Adra.</speaker>
               <l>Amazement! My <hi>Eudoſius</hi> ſtrikes me dumb;</l>
               <l>My Prince, my Brother, and my deareſt Friend,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:96247:11"/>To ſee thee, and embrace thee thus alive,</l>
               <l>Is more than weak humanity can bear.</l>
               <l>Forgive me, Madam, Nature flows ſo high</l>
               <l>That I had almoſt loſt my duty here.
<stage>Kneels.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Oh riſe, <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> we're not now in <hi>Greece;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This poſture ſuits not with our humble ſtate.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Adra.</speaker>
               <l>A thouſand queſtions I have next to ask</l>
               <l>Of my own Love, a thouſand then of yours.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phylante</hi>'s buſy'd with her Rural friends,</l>
               <l>And in our Groves inſtructing 'em to ſing,</l>
               <l>But ſhe ſhall leave her talk to welcome you.
<stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Aurel.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>That ſigh which from thy boſome broke its way,</l>
               <l>Diſcovers thou haſt Secrets in thy heart</l>
               <l>Which ſhake thy inmoſt Soul. Oh ſpeak, my Friend!</l>
               <l>Thou thinkſt perhaps, that in theſe lowly weeds,</l>
               <l>This pomp of eaſe, I dare not look on Fate,</l>
               <l>Nor hear the name of danger, or of death.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Adr.</speaker>
               <l>Oh my <hi>Eudoſius,</hi> 'tis not this which ſwells</l>
               <l>That ſtorm which rages in my breaſt: I know</l>
               <l>You ever were inſenſible of fear:</l>
               <l>Nor is there cauſe of dread in our approach.</l>
               <l>The Emp'ror oft has mourn'd your loſs, and curſt</l>
               <l>His fond compliance with <hi>Placidia</hi>'s will.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>VVhy thoſe unmanly drops than in thy eyes?</l>
               <l>Can I have joys in which thou wilt not ſhare?</l>
               <l>Can I have pleaſures which are none to thee?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Adr.</speaker>
               <l>Yes! you have pleaſures that my Nature loaths;</l>
               <l>To meet you thus a ſtranger to the world,</l>
               <l>Deckt like a Virgin for the Bridal morn,</l>
               <l>To find you thus in wanton Exile live,</l>
               <l>Involv'd in fatal Luxury and Peace.</l>
               <l>Your childiſh train like <hi>Cupids</hi> in our plays,</l>
               <l>Your houſe the Image of the <hi>Paphian</hi> Court,</l>
               <l>Breathing rich odours to debauch your ſence,</l>
               <l>And uſe you to forget your thirſt of Fame.</l>
               <l>Is this d' think delightful to a Friend,</l>
               <l>Who once beheld you in the duſty Field,</l>
               <l>Pierce thro the thickeſt of the Foes of <hi>Greece?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>Did'ſt thou not ſee the viſion, that e'en now</l>
               <l>With dazzling luſtre fill'd this place, which Earth</l>
               <l>Can't equal, nor the ſpangled worlds above?</l>
               <l>Did'ſt thou not ſee her, ſhed her beams on me,</l>
               <l>Her ſweeteſt Influence, and wou'd'ſt thou leave</l>
               <l>Such happineſs, for Empire or for Fame?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ard.</speaker>
               <l>When Love oppoſes Glory, tho 'tis worſe</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:96247:11"/>Than death to quit ſuch fulneſs of delight:</l>
               <l>Yet Fame, Ambition, and your peoples wants,</l>
               <l>Shou'd rouſe you from this Lethargy of eaſe,</l>
               <l>And ſnatch you from the Syrens fatal charm.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>To thee this life, which now thou woud'ſt condemn,</l>
               <l>To thee I owe this exile and this eaſe.</l>
               <l>Thy Counſels firſt inſpir'd me to reſign</l>
               <l>My States to thee, and in ſome diſtant Realm,</l>
               <l>Secure my Princeſs from a Foes embrace.</l>
               <l>By thee my people of my death were told,</l>
               <l>The faith they ow'd to me they've ſworn to thee,</l>
               <l>Nor let thy jealouſy diſturb thy reign,</l>
               <l>'Tis that or Envy urges this reproach.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Adr.</speaker>
               <l>By Heaven you wrong me, I deſpiſe your Throne.</l>
               <l>The Honour of our Houſe, which I prefer</l>
               <l>To Life, or Soveraign Dignity's concern'd;</l>
               <l>And not to ſpeak was to betray my friend.</l>
               <l>But 'tis too late, I ſee you ſtand unmov'd,</l>
               <l>You're deaf to every ſound but ſighs of Love:</l>
               <l>Forgive me, 'tis too bold a truth, I've done.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>Oh my <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> why doſt thou attempt</l>
               <l>To vex my tortur'd mind beyond its force?</l>
               <l>Doſt thou not think the trouble of this day,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aurelia</hi>'s danger, and thy Brother's care,</l>
               <l>Sufficient to ſuppreſs me? Thou ſhalt ſee,</l>
               <l>Inſulted by the Waves of adverſe Fate,</l>
               <l>The Billows all ſhall break away in foam,</l>
               <l>And beat on me as on a ſhoar of Flint;</l>
               <l>But when a future Calm ſerenes our Sky,</l>
               <l>When we have ſported on a Sea of Joy,</l>
               <l>And Peace is to this Land of Love reſtor'd,</l>
               <l>I'll raiſe a Nation here, whoſe name ſhall live,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Greece</hi> ſhall be no more.
<stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Aur. <hi>and</hi> Phyl.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Adr.</speaker>
               <l>There ſpoke the Genius of our Godlike Line.</l>
               <l>But oh! how vain my Reaſons had appear'd,</l>
               <l>Had theſe been here, before whoſe conqu'ring Eyes</l>
               <l>The wiſeſt and the braveſt fall.</l>
               <l>And Love is Truth and Fame.
<stage>
                     <hi>Kneels to</hi> Phyl.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phyl.</speaker>
               <l>Welcome, my Lord, to this bleſt Realm and me.</l>
               <l>To ſee you here, and not to wiſh you well,</l>
               <l>Had I ne're known your merit, had been baſe,</l>
               <l>But to the Brother of a friend I owe—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Adr.</speaker>
               <l>Oh ſay not to the Brother of a Friend;</l>
               <l>You owe to me, your Lover and your Slave,</l>
               <l>All that to years of Conſtancy is due.</l>
               <l>Oh my <hi>Phylante!</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:96247:12"/>
               <speaker>Phyl.</speaker>
               <l>Nay, my Lord, forbear;</l>
               <l>What for the tryal of my Friendſhip's done</l>
               <l>Is what again I'd for <hi>Aurelia</hi> do;</l>
               <l>Our Souls were one before I heard your name,</l>
               <l>And when I ſaw to what ſhe was expos'd,</l>
               <l>Had I abandon'd her to Wilds and Seas,</l>
               <l>To wander o're the pathleſs world alone,</l>
               <l>Say — wou'd you then have thought me worth your heart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Too long you waſte your Minutes in diſpute.</l>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Sileno, <hi>Shepherds and Shepherdeſſes.</hi>
               </stage>
               <l>Behold, my Lord, the Natives of this place,</l>
               <l>With what ſurprize they view your Princely mien.</l>
               <l>The pride of Courts by them unſeen till now.</l>
               <l>Oh happy Ignorance; that never felt</l>
               <l>The ſting of wild Ambition, which will oft,</l>
               <l>Ev'n in theſe humble Manſions vex my Soul.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Sylv. <hi>and Meſſenger.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
               <l>The Emp'ror with his Train are on their way,</l>
               <l>And at the Palace now will ſoon arrive.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sylv.</speaker>
               <l>We are all ready to receive the Court,</l>
               <l>With ſplendour equal to their mighty name.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phyl.</speaker>
               <l>Advance <hi>Sileno,</hi> let the ſports begin,</l>
               <l>We'll have no time to think of future ills.</l>
               <l>The Fury Terror, by our Lays diſarm'd,</l>
               <l>Shall ceaſe to ſting, and fly the Magick ſound.</l>
               <l>For ſhou'd your Muſick be preferr'd to ours,</l>
               <l>The ſighs of Lover to the voice of War:</l>
               <l>Or be the Conqueſt, Shepherds, yours or mine,</l>
               <l>VVe're ſure to triumph o're our Judges both.</l>
            </sp>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="scene">
                        <stage>After a Symphony of Hautboys and Flutes,</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Sileno</speaker>
                           <stage>ſings.</stage>
                           <l>Ye Birds, who in our Foreſts ſing,</l>
                           <l>Ye Winds, that wanton with our Trees,</l>
                           <l>Ye Streams, that murmur to forſake your Spring,</l>
                           <l>Be ſilent, ye outrageous Seas,</l>
                           <l>Attend the Rural Song:</l>
                           <l>'Tis Love's the theme, Love all our Lays employs,</l>
                           <l>Parent of Heavenly Verſe, and heav'nly Joys;</l>
                           <l>With numbers ſoft as their Deſires,</l>
                           <l>With Words and Notes which ſpeak their Fires,</l>
                           <l>He warms the Tuneful Throng.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Then the Trumpets play, and the Kettle-Drums. That over,</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>A Lady</speaker>
                           <stage>ſings.</stage>
                           <pb n="15" facs="tcp:96247:12"/>
                           <l>Ceaſe your Amorous Pipes and Flutes,</l>
                           <l>The Trumpet for the Prize diſputes;</l>
                           <l>The Swains muſt liſten to a loftier ſound,</l>
                           <l>You only flatter their deſpair,</l>
                           <l>The Trumpet drives away their Care,</l>
                           <l>And makes 'em languiſh for a nobler wound.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Sileno.</speaker>
                           <l>Hark! what frightful notes I hear,</l>
                           <l>Which Eccho is tormented to reply;</l>
                           <l>The trembling Sheep and Shepherds fly;</l>
                           <l>The Plain and Mountain ſtruck with deadly fear;</l>
                           <l>This Clangor ſure was made for Death;</l>
                           <l>Our Pipes and Flutes have no ſuch fatal breath.</l>
                           <l>They eaſe our Pains, they ſooth our Care;</l>
                           <l>Theſe ſounds wou'd drive us to Deſpair;</l>
                           <l>Forbear the dreadful notes, forbear.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Flutes and Hautboys again.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Shepherd.</speaker>
                           <l>See, the trembling Sheep revive,</l>
                           <l>The Shepherds ſeem again to live.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Shepherdſs.</speaker>
                           <l>Theſe gentle murmurs ſuit our Shades,</l>
                           <l>And beſt our Paſſions move;</l>
                           <l>With pity they inſpire our Maids,</l>
                           <l>And teach our Youth to Love.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                           <l>Theſe gentle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Hautboys and Flutes again.</stage>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>You both have happily perform'd your part,</l>
               <l>By one tranſported, by another charm'd,</l>
               <l>You both excell'd by turns.
<stage>a March is heard.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>Again the noble Clangor rends our Caves,</l>
               <l>And tells us our Imperial Gueſt is nigh,</l>
               <l>This the important hour on which depends</l>
               <l>Our laſting Peace, and this begins with ſmiles.</l>
               <l>Oh may't not prove, as we have ſometimes ſeen,</l>
               <l>A ſtormy noon ſucceed a chearful morn?</l>
               <l>But why ſhou'd we the worſt of fortune fear,</l>
               <l>Love was our crime, and Love is maſter here.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Ex. Omnes.</stage>
            <trailer>End of the Second Act.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="act">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:96247:13"/>
            <head>ACT III.</head>
            <stage>Scene a Hall of the Palace, Repreſenting the Court of <hi>Pan.</hi>
            </stage>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="scene">
                        <stage>
                           <hi>After the Song of Fame is over,</hi> Pan <hi>riſes (while the Muſick plays) in a Wood, being ſeveral rows of Trees illuminated. All the Actors on the Stage, A Warlike Tune.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Fame.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>THro wondring Worlds I</hi> Caeſar<hi>'s worth proclaim,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>The Nations tremble at his mighty name:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>My hundred Tongues his matchleſs deeds declare,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>In Peace his Wiſdom, or his Force in War.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Himſelf at reſt, my Labours never ceaſe</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>To ſpread his Vertues, or in War or Peace.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pan.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>What voice is this, to me unknown,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>What noiſe, which in the</hi> Elyſian <hi>Shades</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Diſturbs my quiet Reign?</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>If God or Goddeſs, hence be gone,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Nor vex our Youth, nor fright our Maids,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>But leave to me the Plain;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>I know thee by thy hundred Tongues,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Thy hundred Ears, and thouſand Eyes,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>To Court go ſing thy flatt'ring Songs,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Among the Great diſperſe thy Lyes,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Nor raiſe Confuſion in our peaceful Land.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>And you, who reign with</hi> Pan <hi>below,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Aſcend; and ye who rove in Wilds,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Or preſs the Vine, or watch in Fields,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Who uſe the Crook, or bend the Bow,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Appear at my Command.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Satyr, Shepherds, Shepherdeſſes, Bacchanalian, Hunters, Huntreſſes.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Hunters and Huntreſſes.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>We come from the Mountain, and hunting the Fox.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Shepherds and Shepherdeſſes.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>And we from the Valley, and keeping our Flocks.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>I come from the Foreſt, and plucking up Trees.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Bacchanalian.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>And I from the Wine-preſs, and ſucking fat Lees.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>At</hi> Pan <hi>s great Command we leave Working and Play,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                                    <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                                 </gap> call, which with Joy we obey.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>
                           <pb n="17" facs="tcp:96247:13"/>Ceres <hi>aſcends.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Ceres.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Where's my</hi> Pan, <hi>my Lord, my Love,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Why flies he from the Sacred Grove,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Why flies he from his</hi> Ceres <hi>arms,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>For mortal Beauty, leave immortal Charms?</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pan.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>One of the Gods, who rule on Earth,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Deſcends to viſit now the Plain;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>For him we bring forth all our mirth;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>For him too ſummon you your Train.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Our Preſence ſhall their Rural Triumphs grace,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>And with celeſtial luſtre fill the place.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Ceres.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Ye Men and Maids, who cut the Ear,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Or bind the bounteous Sheave,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Who reap the Golden Meads appear,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>A while your Labour leave.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Binders and Reapers.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Reap.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Ous work at an end, we'll awhile go to play,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>To Binding and Reaping a much better way.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>This Harveſt thus in, for the next we will Plow,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>And if we expect a new Crop we muſt Sow.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Bind.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Not ſo haſty, you're too warm;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Thus all Renters for a year,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>When they mean to leave a Farm,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Care not what they wear or tear.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Come — Man, ſince you are ſo ſtout,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Take a Leaſe on't, and be merry,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>There's no fear you'll wear it out,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>When you are oblig'd to tarry.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Reap.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Oh talk not of Leaſes, I hate 'em, my Honey,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Your Copy Lands are for men who have Money.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>When I rent at my will, I can do as I pleaſe;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>And had much rather</hi> Hold <hi>by another mans Leaſe.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Bind.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>You and I ſhall never deal,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Put an end then to the ſtrife,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Give me both your Hand and Seal,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>And the Soil is yours for Life.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Reap.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>By my troth 'tis too hard, as the Taxes go now,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>When my Landlord paid all, we more freely could ſow;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>But ſince I have try'd it, and know how 'twill bear,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>'Tis a bargain between us.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Bind.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>For Life.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Reap.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>For a Year.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>For two Voices.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pan <hi>&amp;</hi> Ceres.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Plenty, mirth and gay delights,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Pleaſant days, and bliſsful nights;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>All the ſweets of Love and Peace,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="18" facs="tcp:96247:14"/>
                              <hi>Numerous Flocks and large Increaſe,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Ever bleſs you, Joy attend ye,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Pan <hi>and</hi> Ceres <hi>ſtill befriend ye,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>While they deſcend <hi>Fame</hi> appears. The Trumpet ſounds.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Fame.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Away with all theſe fatal Charms,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Away with theſe deluding Sounds,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>The notes that rouze the fearful Camp to Arms,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>That from the Coward drive his falſe alarms,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>And make him dauntleſs look on death and wounds.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Fame to theſe Woods again reſtores,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>And with the Emp'rors potent name torments the lab'ring Shores.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <stage>While the Muſick is performing, <hi>Arcadius</hi> ſeems to talk very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly with <hi>Parmenio</hi> and <hi>Nicias.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>Obſerve, <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> how <hi>Arcadius</hi> ſtands,</l>
               <l>Unmov'd by Harmony, or Artful ſhew:</l>
               <l>Ev'n I who trembling on the brink of fate,</l>
               <l>Behold the horrid Precipice, am charm'd.</l>
               <l>What cares are his ſuperiour then to mine?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>The Emp'ror, weary'd with the days fatigue,</l>
               <l>Wills, that all leave him but the Prince of <hi>Thrace.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Ex. Om. but</hi> Arc. Ad. Par. <hi>and</hi> Nic.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>That I have cauſe to think I am betray'd,</l>
               <l>This wealth, with which our own can ſcarce compare</l>
               <l>Theſe Tow'rs, theſe rich Alcoves, theſe Gilded Roofs,</l>
               <l>And all this bright magnificence declare.</l>
               <l>Is this the dwelling of a private Swain?</l>
               <l>This the retreat of diſcontent and love?</l>
               <l>The Mines of <hi>Aſia,</hi> and the <hi>Ethiop</hi> Sands;</l>
               <l>Scarce in the courſe of ten abundant years,</l>
               <l>Produce more Treaſures than my Eyes behold.</l>
               <l>I ſee you know the Maſter of this place,</l>
               <l>Already grown his confident and friend.</l>
               <l>You have your ſecrets and your private talk,</l>
               <l>While I with Fairy Dance and Song amus'd,</l>
               <l>Play with my danger, as the Pilot ſteers</l>
               <l>Tow'rds the ſweet Voice which tempts him to the Rock.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Adr.</speaker>
               <l>Yourſelf, my Lord, diſcover'd firſt his worth,</l>
               <l>You, who ſo ſoon advanc'd him to a Throne,</l>
               <l>Might well expect th' admiring world would gaze</l>
               <l>With more than common pleaſure on the man,</l>
               <l>Whom, from profoundeſt ſolitude, you choſe</l>
               <l>To wear a Scepter, and to ſit with Kings.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>This ſolitude ſo gloriouſly adorn'd,</l>
               <l>Theſe Riches hidden in a Diamond Cave,</l>
               <l>Might tempt a Hermits Faith, and make him view</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:96247:14"/>The Empire of the world with luſtful Eyes,</l>
               <l>Nor dropt they like you gay Machines from Heav'n,</l>
               <l>Nor is it painted Wealth, but Maſſy Gold.</l>
               <l>Have you not heard him boaſt his high deſcent.</l>
               <l>What Princeſs, careleſs of her Nuptial Vow,</l>
               <l>Has bred this Iſſue of polluted Love,</l>
               <l>To nouriſh Treaſon here, and prove at laſt</l>
               <l>Her injur'd Monarch's ruin, and his ſhame?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Adr.</speaker>
               <l>This of a Prince? and underneath his Roof?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>You're toucht, Sir, and would tell me this is baſe</l>
               <l>Ingrate, Inhoſpitable, and unjuſt,</l>
               <l>Your Eyes convict you, and your glowing Cheeks</l>
               <l>Burn with projected Miſchiefs.</l>
               <l>But Princes muſt not trifle with their Fate,</l>
               <l>From whence this Rural prodigy? What Realm</l>
               <l>Cou'd ſpare the Treaſure that ſupports this Coſt?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Adr.</speaker>
               <l>He told you whence himſelf,</l>
               <l>From this bleſt Land where Peace and Safety dwell,</l>
               <l>Where no projected miſchiefs e're were form'd.</l>
               <l>No Princeſs, careleſs of her Nuptial Vow,</l>
               <l>E're thought to wrong her Monarch, or prophane</l>
               <l>This Vale of innocence with lawleſs love.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>The ſecret which you dare not truſt with me,</l>
               <l>Is brooding miſchiefs of the blackeſt form.</l>
               <l>Prince! you're my Pris'ner till the truth is known.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Adr.</speaker>
               <l>Is this the ſafety of an Emp'rors Faith?</l>
               <l>But that the Crown which glitters on your brow</l>
               <l>Commands ſubmiſſion, and forbids my arm</l>
               <l>The vengeance to a Soveraigns honour due,</l>
               <l>Theſe chains ſhou'd never elſe affront your name,</l>
               <l>My ſelf wou'd elſe be Guardian of your Oath,</l>
               <l>And force you to be juſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>Guards! till you hear from us obſerve the Prince;</l>
               <l>To all but thoſe whom we allow, defend</l>
               <l>Admittance near him, 'tis our lifes concern.
<stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Nic. <hi>with</hi> Adr.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Next him, by whom I reign, I know no pow'r</l>
               <l>Superiour to my own. No Judge, who durſt</l>
               <l>Declare againſt my pleaſure that is wrong,</l>
               <l>Which the Imperial word pronounces right.</l>
               <l>I for this deed can anſwer to my ſelf,</l>
               <l>The world muſt then be ſatisfy'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis evident, the Treaſon's grown mature.</l>
               <l>What Intereſt has <hi>Adraſtus</hi> in this man?</l>
               <l>This riſing Comet, whoſe portentous look</l>
               <l>To Nations threatens ruin.</l>
               <l>Is this the Manſion of a Village, Lord?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:96247:15"/>The <hi>Roman</hi> Chiefs, in their triumphal pride,</l>
               <l>Were never more illuſtrious in their ſports,</l>
               <l>Than thoſe ev'n now with wonder I behold.</l>
               <l>The Prince, by nature, turbulent and proud,</l>
               <l>Brooks not the narrow limits of his <hi>Thrace;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With envy he beheld <hi>Byzantium</hi>'s wealth,</l>
               <l>When for his Brother, with opprobrious terms,</l>
               <l>He wou'd have forc'd your Daughter from your arms.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>Oh! thou haſt rous'd a fury in my breaſt,</l>
               <l>Which ſtings me worſe than Scorpions fiery tongues.</l>
               <l>Why didſt thou name my Daughter? ſhe was once</l>
               <l>The bleſſing of my Youth,</l>
               <l>The glory of my Court,</l>
               <l>The faireſt product of <hi>Pulcheria</hi>'s Love:</l>
               <l>But now a wanderer in ſome barren Clime;</l>
               <l>Driv'n by my cruelty to ſpend her Spring,</l>
               <l>With a vile raviſher in want and pain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis time, my Lord, to think of this no more,</l>
               <l>What we can't help we muſt with patience bear,</l>
               <l>And when you're thus by threatning dangers preſt,</l>
               <l>Look forwards to prevent the future ills.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>What wou'd'ſt thou that we do? I yet can ſee</l>
               <l>No ills, but ſuch as from ſuſpicion riſe.</l>
               <l>Perhaps as Idle as <hi>Adraſtus</hi> threats.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>In <hi>Rome,</hi> 'twas whiſper'd that <hi>Byzantium</hi>'s Streets</l>
               <l>With <hi>Thracian</hi> Captains ſwarm'd, and <hi>Thracian</hi> arms,</l>
               <l>Your ſelf has heard the Rumours which have ſpread.</l>
               <l>Of Armies on the Borders to revenge</l>
               <l>An injur'd Brother, true—the rumours dy'd,</l>
               <l>But ſtill the Injury, as they tell you, lives.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>Again, thy juſt reproaches rack my Soul;</l>
               <l>To what wou'd'ſt thou perſwade me?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>To be ſafe.</l>
               <l>The buſineſs of my days, my nightly care</l>
               <l>Is to preſerve you from the ſtrokes,</l>
               <l>Of ſuch as dare not meet you in the Field.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>What plots haſt thou diſcover'd?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>None, my Lord?</l>
               <l>Howe'er, I thought it ſtrange to ſee the Prince</l>
               <l>Abandon <hi>Thrace,</hi> and hear <hi>Amintor</hi>'s name</l>
               <l>So often chanted in your ears with praiſe:</l>
               <l>Nor were his Friends contented till their pray'rs</l>
               <l>Extorted from your bounty what 'tis plain,</l>
               <l>They meant to take without your gift, a Crown.</l>
               <l>Why, when this Journey was at firſt propos'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:96247:15"/>Were there ſuch reaſons giv'n you to adjourn</l>
               <l>The viſit, or diſſwade you from't? And when</l>
               <l>He ſaw you wou'd not liſten to him. Why</l>
               <l>Muſt he be foremoſt, was he not afraid,</l>
               <l>His friends might be ſurpriz'd, or unprepar'd.</l>
               <l>It may be only Fancy, but if e're</l>
               <l>My Loyalty foreſaw a black deſign,</l>
               <l>And was of ſervice to your Empire, now</l>
               <l>This very hour, the wit of Hell's at work,</l>
               <l>And you're the deſtin'd Victim.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>Heav'n! he ſhakes</l>
               <l>With honeſt fears, do with me what thou wilt,</l>
               <l>We'll to the City, arm the <hi>Roman</hi> bands,</l>
               <l>And ſtorm the Palace in the face of noon.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Adr.</speaker>
               <l>No, 'tis not worth your care, command your Guard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>To ſeize on every Poſt which may oppoſe</l>
               <l>Aſſiſtance from the Province. This at firſt</l>
               <l>They muſt with utmoſt ſecrecy perform;</l>
               <l>While I by promis'd Tortures and Rewards,</l>
               <l>Diſcover from <hi>Amintor</hi>'s Slaves, how long</l>
               <l>Their Lord has known the Prince of <hi>Thrace,</hi> and whence</l>
               <l>Their Maſter, and this Maſs of Riches came.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>Be careful of my name, nor let the world</l>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Re-enter</hi> Nic.</stage>
               <l>Report my Hoſt inſulted by his Gueſt,</l>
               <l>On groundleſs Tales, and viſionary Fears.</l>
               <l>I'll give directions to my Guards: The reſt</l>
               <l>Is left to thee. Be wiſe.
<stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Alc.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>Be ſo your ſelf, fond Emp'ror!</l>
               <l>Was not your Reaſon clouded by your fears,</l>
               <l>The Tyrant paſſion of your Soul, you ſoon</l>
               <l>Wou'd ſee thro all my airy Plots; and Truth</l>
               <l>And Innocence wou'd ſhine like perfect day.</l>
               <l>Well, <hi>Nicias!</hi> thou, I know art pleas'd to ſee</l>
               <l>The hour, for which we oft have wiſht to find.</l>
               <l>The Lord of <hi>Greece</hi> from Foreign Counſels free,</l>
               <l>Conſents to hear his Friends, and own their Love:</l>
               <l>How ſuits Confinement with <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> ſay?</l>
               <l>Does he not rage, and like a Forreſt Boar</l>
               <l>Entangled in the Snare, by raging cloſe</l>
               <l>The toil the faſter on him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>Yes!</l>
               <l>A while; his wild reſentment threaten'd VVar.</l>
               <l>And with injurious words, denounc'd to <hi>Greece</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Eternal Enmity: But moſt to you.</l>
               <l>The Emp'ror and the Empire's ruin. This</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:96247:16"/>He oft repeated in outrageous Phraſe,</l>
               <l>And darted from his Eyes avengeful fires.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>I laugh to hear him talk of War in Chains.</l>
               <l>His Fury's impotent, his Sword is mine,</l>
               <l>He lives, but till my Love has full revenge,</l>
               <l>And reacht <hi>Phylante</hi>'s Image in his heart.</l>
               <l>Oh! thou remembreſt when the cruel Maid,</l>
               <l>Deaf to my ſighs, and heedleſs of my tears,</l>
               <l>Profuſely on him laviſht guilty ſmiles,</l>
               <l>And ſpurn'd me from her feet with utmoſt ſcorn.</l>
               <l>The curſt remembrance of that ſhameful hour,</l>
               <l>Is fatal to my Foe— He dies.</l>
               <l>Nor can <hi>Arcadius</hi> ſave him, 'tis too late;</l>
               <l>Tho as he's won't, he ſhou'd this minute change,</l>
               <l>His breach of Treaty's ne're to be compos'd,</l>
               <l>But to be ſafe, the Prince of <hi>Thrace</hi> muſt dye,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>Or <hi>Greece</hi> muſt periſh by inteſtine broils,</l>
               <l>Brothers by Brothers fall, and Friends by Freinds,</l>
               <l>Which to prevent—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>Ay <hi>Nicias,</hi> that's my task.</l>
               <l>To hinder this the <hi>Thracian</hi> Prince muſt bleed,</l>
               <l>The Emp'ror ſeize his State.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>For what?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>That's left</l>
               <l>To me, and if my Vengeance proves ſo weak,</l>
               <l>It can't find reaſons for his death, 'tis juſt</l>
               <l>My wrongs unpuniſht ſhould be ſtill my ſhame.</l>
               <l>I know thee, faithful <hi>Nicias,</hi> that with thee,</l>
               <l>My moſt important ſecrets are ſecure.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Amintor,</hi> or whatever elſe he's ſtil'd,</l>
               <l>When his Friends ſafety calls, perhaps may arm</l>
               <l>The Province h'as obtain'd, but what he meant</l>
               <l>Of ſervice to the Prince ſhall prove his doom.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Roman</hi> Guards at ſeveral Poſts are plac'd,</l>
               <l>To quell the Village Tumults in their riſe.</l>
               <l>Thy charge, of higheſt moment, is within:</l>
               <l>Let none without the Imperial Signet ſee</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> 'twill enrage him yet the more,</l>
               <l>And that the more encreaſe the Emp'rors fears,</l>
               <l>On which my hopes depend.
<stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Eud. <hi>and</hi> Alca.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>N c.</speaker>
               <l>My Lord, our Hoſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>Retire, expect anon</l>
               <l>Inſtructions further from me.</l>
               <l>My buſineſs now is not with him, but yet</l>
               <l>Tis criminal to love the man I hate.
<stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Par. <hi>&amp;</hi> Nic.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:96247:16"/>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>Confin'd, without my knowledge, in my houſe,</l>
               <l>Againſt the faith of Nations and of Leagues;</l>
               <l>From thee who never didſt deceive me. This</l>
               <l>Wou'd ſcarce be credible, but that the looks</l>
               <l>Of him, who there avoided us, declare</l>
               <l>The guilt of wicked Counſels, and confirm
<stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Aurelia.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Thy juſt report, and make our danger ſure.</l>
               <l>Oh my <hi>Aurelia!</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Tell me why that ſigh?</l>
               <l>Is it for me thy nature's on the rack?</l>
               <l>For me, that theſe Convulſions ſhake thy Soul.</l>
               <l>Oh let me ſhare the anguiſh of thy mind</l>
               <l>Say—We muſt dye — Alas! I know we muſt,</l>
               <l>And in my Crime rejoyce, my Love of thee.</l>
               <l>Fate in thy Brother has begun her ſpoils,</l>
               <l>Our Lot I know is next.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>Oh ceaſe thy tears.</l>
               <l>And if 'tis in thy heart to love me leſs,</l>
               <l>In pity to us both attempt it now:</l>
               <l>For while I ſee thee thus endearing kind,</l>
               <l>I grow a Coward, and cou'd wiſh to live.</l>
               <l>Think of the Glories thou haſt left, the worlds</l>
               <l>That would have kneel'd before thee but for me.</l>
               <l>Think of the heats that oft have parcht thy limbs,</l>
               <l>The tedious nights which we have liv'd in Snow,</l>
               <l>The Tempeſts which have toſt thee on the Main,</l>
               <l>The hateful Exile thou haſt ſince endur'd,</l>
               <l>The terrours that aſſault thee. Think on this,</l>
               <l>And then behold me as the cauſe of all.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Oh! I for ever cou'd behold thee thus.</l>
               <l>For ever feaſt my longing eyes on thine.</l>
               <l>Thee, the laſt object that ſhall bleſs their Rayes,</l>
               <l>And give my parting Soul a taſte of heav'n;</l>
               <l>For heav'n, they tell us, is but perfect Love,</l>
               <l>And mine's perfection when I look on thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>Why, when my care preſag'd this dreadful hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Why did my Brother bring us hopes of peace,</l>
               <l>Or that thy Father would forgive our flight,</l>
               <l>When thou the darling of his age were't found?</l>
               <l>Oh thou art found to him, but loſt to me.</l>
               <l>The fatal ſecret's known, my Friend in Chains,</l>
               <l>This, this, <hi>Aurelia,</hi> racks me worſe than Wheels:</l>
               <l>I've liv'd a Slave too long, a worthleſs Slave,</l>
               <l>I've ſeen my Brother injur'd to my face,</l>
               <l>And Patient of his bonds expect my own.</l>
               <l>Wou'd I in <hi>Thrace</hi> have ſuffer'd this from Kings?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:96247:17"/>My houſe by Foreign pow'rs prophan'd.</l>
               <l>Has he then mockt me with a Soveraigns name,</l>
               <l>The word that ſaid it was the voice of Heav'n</l>
               <l>Pronounc'd by him, and here 'tis mine to Reign?</l>
               <l>Oh, had th' <hi>Arabian</hi> Hoſt beheld me thus,</l>
               <l>Thus paſſive in my wrongs, they ne're had fled</l>
               <l>From <hi>Thracian</hi> Arms, nor ſhunn'd the Victors Sword.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Ceaſe the remembrance of that glorious day,</l>
               <l>Talk not of War, your buſineſs is with Love.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>My buſineſs is with Death?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Oh! ſpeak, my Lord,</l>
               <l>You think too much on things which long are paſt,</l>
               <l>I'll to my Father, tell him of our Loves.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>And beg him, wou'dſt thou not to let us live,</l>
               <l>By Heav'n, I ſcorn to owe my Life to one,</l>
               <l>Who can't defend his own,</l>
               <l>I'll give my Brother liberty or dye,</l>
               <l>Nor wou'd I yield to live till he is free?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alcander</hi> to <hi>Dametas</hi>—Let him know</l>
               <l>Our danger, 'tis enough, and tell his Friends</l>
               <l>That if we want their aid, they be prepar'd
<stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Alc.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Come, my <hi>Aurelia!</hi> See, my Fury's o're,</l>
               <l>And I am gentle now as Lovers dreams.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>With you indeed 'tis but a dream to love,</l>
               <l>Which waking, you forget, or bluſh to own.</l>
               <l>Off—Off—I dare not gaze, for never man</l>
               <l>Could look ſo much like truth, and be ſo falſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>Oh why this language, to my ear unknown;</l>
               <l>By thee too left, I'm wretched then indeed.</l>
               <l>Come — While this minute is our own, and whoſe</l>
               <l>The next ſhall be, or where we next ſhall meet,</l>
               <l>Is only known to Fate. While this is ours,</l>
               <l>Come — Let us ſpend it like the reſt in love.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>That word from thee's like ſounds of empty air.</l>
               <l>Love always beſt is in obedience ſeen.</l>
               <l>Had I been dear to thee, thou ne're hadſt thought</l>
               <l>Of War, nor mention'd it againſt my Will,</l>
               <l>And who's this Foe with whom thou wou'd'ſt contend</l>
               <l>The Father of thy Wife,</l>
               <l>Thy Emp'ror and thy Gueſt.</l>
               <l>From thee by Guards and Troops of Slaves ſecur'd,</l>
               <l>And what wou'd'ſt thou oppoſe to this, a band</l>
               <l>Of Village Heroes arm'd with Crooks and Staves.</l>
               <l>Wer't thou in <hi>Thrace,</hi> thy Armies on their march</l>
               <l>Led on by thee and <hi>Greece,</hi> the deſtin'd Prize.</l>
               <l>Doſt think thy Feudatory Realm, a Match</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:96247:17"/>For the great Empire of the world.</l>
               <l>Had I been dear to thee, as thou haſt ſworn,</l>
               <l>Thou wou'd'ſt not to offend me act like one</l>
               <l>Whom Reaſon has forſook.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>Was I in <hi>Thrace,</hi> my Armies on their march,</l>
               <l>And the great Empire of the world the Prize,</l>
               <l>Thus govern'd, I ſhould think of <hi>Philip</hi>'s Son,</l>
               <l>Who with a choſen few ſubdu'd the Eaſt,</l>
               <l>And made the proud <hi>Euphrates</hi> flow with Blood.</l>
               <l>But in this peaceful Region, where I ſee</l>
               <l>A Prize much fairer than the ſubject World,</l>
               <l>What wou'd I not?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Thy Eyes ſpeak what thou wou'd'ſt, and they are truth,</l>
               <l>They force belief beyond a thouſand Oaths.</l>
               <l>We wander in the dark, miſled by fear;</l>
               <l>For was the ſecret known, thy ſelf wou'd firſt</l>
               <l>My Fathers Vengeance feel, if Vengeance ſtill</l>
               <l>Is in his breaſt reſerv'd; of him inform'd.</l>
               <l>For what <hi>Adraſtus</hi> ſuffers, you may then;</l>
               <l>Or arm, or ſue for Peace, as we reſolve.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>We all diſpute in vain with what we love.</l>
               <l>I'll to <hi>Arcadius,</hi> ſhew him how this deed</l>
               <l>VVill ever be injurious to his Fame.</l>
               <l>Thou to <hi>Phylante,</hi> and forget thy griefs,</l>
               <l>To leſſen hers, who now abounds in woe.</l>
               <l>Theſe dangers cannot long our Loves moleſt,</l>
               <l>For death or pardon ſoon muſt bring us reſt.
<stage>Ex. Omnes.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <trailer>End of the Third Act.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="act">
            <head>ACT IV.</head>
            <stage>Scene an Apartment before that where <hi>Adraſtus</hi> is confin'd.</stage>
            <stage>Aurelia, Phylante, Sileno, Myrtilla, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>WHere will your ſorrow lead you? Can your tears</l>
               <l>O're doors of Braſs prevail, or Marble Walls,</l>
               <l>Or Savage man, leſs flexible than theſe?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis yet imperfect night, and all is huſht,</l>
               <l>As if her time was ſpent, and day was nigh.</l>
               <l>What means this early quiet, when our ſhades,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:96247:18"/>Converted to a Court, ſhou'd ring with noiſe,</l>
               <l>VVhich waits on Princes, and proclaims their ſtate?</l>
               <l>The hours that labour with our Fate are vext</l>
               <l>To bring the dreadful iſſue forth, and lag</l>
               <l>Behind their courſe. Forgive me, I am rude,</l>
               <l>My ſenſes wand'ring make me hear your words,</l>
               <l>As things which came not from a Friend like you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>To ſpeak you comfort, is I know in vain,</l>
               <l>All Counſel in exceſs of trouble's loſt.</l>
               <l>But what can you propoſe by coming here;</l>
               <l>Tis death for theſe to let you ſee the Prince:</l>
               <l>Or was it not, while you believe him ſafe,</l>
               <l>A minutes abſence you may well endure.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phyl.</speaker>
               <l>An age for you I ſuffer'd with content,</l>
               <l>An age of abſence for my friend; but then</l>
               <l>I thought him ſafe, and wou'd not wiſh for more.</l>
               <l>My eyes have ſeen him ſince, the pleaſure's new,</l>
               <l>And I again muſt ſee him, or I dye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>You will, on us th' impending ſtorm will fall,</l>
               <l>VVith us the Emp'rors wrath will end, with us</l>
               <l>His bounds and your deſpair will be no more.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phyl.</speaker>
               <l>For you my heart weeps blood as well as him.</l>
               <l>My Pity thus divided, ſcarce can tell</l>
               <l>Where firſt ſhe ſhould her mournful office pay.</l>
               <l>She's us'd to viſit you, the ſtranger claims</l>
               <l>His debt, and with a voice which will be heard.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>You've reaſon, was it in your pow'r to act,</l>
               <l>The Guards remov'd, the reſt you might o'recome.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Soft muſick begins here, and continues till the other is perform'd.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phyl.</speaker>
               <l>And theſe we'll conquer with the reſt, if 'tis</l>
               <l>In Numbers, or in Notes to win on man.</l>
               <l>We'll move their hearts to liſten to our pray'r,</l>
               <l>And when they're moſt defenceleſs tempt their faith.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>On Souls diſpos'd to yield you may ſucceed,</l>
               <l>But few will venture where the crime is death.</l>
               <l>This ſooner will betray 'em from their truſt,</l>
               <l>My Fathers Signet which I brought from <hi>Greece,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That ſerv'd us in our flight, if pray'rs ſhould ſail,</l>
               <l>Produce it at the Emp'rors dread command.</l>
               <l>Be ſpeedy in your Enterprize, and learn</l>
               <l>From whence this violence aroſe, and how</l>
               <l>We may, if poſſible, prevent its growth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis fatal to expoſe this Signet here,</l>
               <l>Put ſtill more fatal to remain in doubt.</l>
               <l>I'll try by ſofter means to make my way,</l>
               <l>This the laſt method I'll attempt to uſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:96247:18"/>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>I ſee 'tis time to leave you, and to heav'n</l>
               <l>VVill lift my vows, to proſper your deſign
<stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Aur.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phyl.</speaker>
               <l>Ye fair companions of my better days!</l>
               <l>Come, miniſter your aid in my diſtreſs,</l>
               <l>And with your tuneful airs compoſe my mind.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>She lies on a Couch, Muſick plays louder, Scene opens and diſcovers</hi> Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias <hi>and Guards waiting on</hi> Adraſtus</stage>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="scene">
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Shepherdeſs.</speaker>
                           <l>UNderneath a Gloomy Shade,</l>
                           <l>By an antient Poplar made,</l>
                           <l>While the Zephyrs round her play,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Clotis</hi> thus complaining lay,</l>
                           <l>Where ſhall I <hi>Philander</hi> find?</l>
                           <l>Eccho anſwer'd her, <hi>Behind.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Thrice ſhe turn'd and ſaw 'twas falſe,</l>
                           <l>Curſing Ecchoes lying tales,</l>
                           <l>Thus ſhe mourn'd again, and ſaid,</l>
                           <l>Where is my <hi>Philander</hi> fled?</l>
                           <l>From his Flocks, his Friends and Me;</l>
                           <l>When ſhall I my Lover ſee,</l>
                           <l>Whither turn to find him out?</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Eccho anſwer'd her,</hi> About.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Shepherd.</speaker>
                           <l>By Eccho thus mockt, on a Bank ſhe reclines,</l>
                           <l>Reſolv'd ne're to truſt her complaint to the winds,</l>
                           <l>Till <hi>Cupid,</hi> who pity'd her Sorrow and Tears,</l>
                           <l>On the wings of a Dove to aſſiſt her appears.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Cupid <hi>is ſeen the Air.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cupid.</speaker>
                           <l>Love deſcends at your complaint,</l>
                           <l>He who knows what moſt you want.</l>
                           <l>Bids you to the Cave repair,</l>
                           <l>Where you us'd to vent your care,</l>
                           <l>You ſhall find your Lover there.</l>
                           <l>Bound by mighty <hi>Pan</hi> he lies,</l>
                           <l>Piercing with his grief the Skies.</l>
                           <l>There with your Companions go,</l>
                           <l>Try what Virgin Songs will do.</l>
                           <l>The force of Youth and Beauty try,</l>
                           <l>And <hi>Pan</hi> will yield as well as I.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Shepherd.</speaker>
                           <l>We'll go the Cave where the Shepherd in Chains</l>
                           <l>Lies wrongfully puniſh'd for Crimes he abhors;</l>
                           <l>With our Layes we'll endeavour to leſſen his pains,</l>
                           <l>And pleaſe him with ſinging the name he adores.</l>
                           <l>'Tis <hi>Cloris,</hi> who loves him, the <hi>Cloris</hi> he loves,</l>
                           <l>Who muſt uſe all her art to obtain him relief;</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="28" facs="tcp:96247:19"/>
                              <hi>But ſhe'll uſe it in vain, for her Harmony moves</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Rocks only and Trees, and the Tyrant's ſtill deaf.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Shepherdeſs.</speaker>
                           <l>Happy, ever happy we,</l>
                           <l>Cou'd we ſee <hi>Philander</hi> free.</l>
                           <l>Love, the beſt and ſweeteſt Care,</l>
                           <l>Is our only Torment here</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>The Ghoſt of</hi> Orpheus <hi>ariſes.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>
                              <hi>Ghoſt of</hi> Orpheus.</speaker>
                           <l>In vain, fair Nymph, with your Celeſtial art,</l>
                           <l>You ſtrive to move a Mortal's heart.</l>
                           <l>Ev'n I, whoſe Muſick huſht the roar of Hell,</l>
                           <l>And made her Fiends forget their Pains,</l>
                           <l>When not one hideous groan, nor yell,</l>
                           <l>Was heard throughout the <hi>Stygian</hi> Plains,</l>
                           <l>Whoſe voice to things inſenſible was known,</l>
                           <l>And dancing Woods confeſt its wondrous pow'r;</l>
                           <l>I ne're could humane rage repel,</l>
                           <l>But by the Monſters fury fell,</l>
                           <l>Which often does her firſt begot, and darling Sons devour.</l>
                           <l>Ceaſe your Heavenly notes a while,</l>
                           <l>You will ſoon your Lover ſee,</l>
                           <l>Keep your Songs till fate ſhall ſmile.</l>
                           <l>Fate has told you this by me.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                           <l>Haſte, ye happy minutes, haſte,</l>
                           <l>To <hi>Cloris</hi> her Lover reſtore;</l>
                           <l>And grant us, ye Gods, when this danger is paſt,</l>
                           <l>That <hi>Pan</hi> may torment us no more.</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis all Enchantment, every thing I ſee,</l>
               <l>And hear, and meet tranſports me, or I dream,</l>
               <l>Or I have ſeen that Angel form before;</l>
               <l>A fairer ſure I never ſaw, nor heard</l>
               <l>Such ſounds in <hi>Greece,</hi> where firſt the Lyre was ſtrung.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <l>You ſeem ſurpriz'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>And who without ſurprize</l>
               <l>Can hear ſuch harmony, or look on you.</l>
               <l>I thought in woods to meet with none but Nymphs</l>
               <l>Of humble make, and here I find a choire</l>
               <l>Of Beauties, who may well adorn a Court.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <l>This language in a Soldier we excuſe,</l>
               <l>Their words, like their profeſſion, ſhould be rough,</l>
               <l>And when you ſpeak us fair, we women think</l>
               <l>'Tis meant to do us wrong.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>To ſuch as you,</l>
               <l>'Tis equally impoſſible to ſpeak</l>
               <l>In harſher phraſe, or mean to do you wrong.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <l>If by your talk I might your temper gueſs,</l>
               <l>I rather ſhould believe you'd help our Sex,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:96247:19"/>That begg'd a ſervice of you, tho it lookt</l>
               <l>Like danger, than diſmiſs 'em with reproach.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>For you, whate'er you ask, by heav'n! 'tis done,</l>
               <l>My Maſter's honour, and his life ſecur'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <l>My buſineſs is within.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>Ha! I'm betray'd.</l>
               <l>Madam, my Oath's ſtill unprofan'd and you —</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <l>Deny'd — what leſs could I expect from man,</l>
               <l>Than with one breath to ſwear, and be forſworn.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>My Maſters honour, and his life ſecur'd,</l>
               <l>I ſwear again, whate're you ask, 'tis done.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <l>How if I ſaw the Prince, wou'd that concern</l>
               <l>Your Maſters honour or his ſafety?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>Both.</l>
               <l>His honour in my breach of his Command,</l>
               <l>His ſafety in my ſerving of his Foe.
<stage>Shews the Signet.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <l>This then is his command.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>Which I obey.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <l>I try'd your Loyalty, and found you true.</l>
               <l>The Royal word that order'd this, forbids</l>
               <l>Such liberty to all but me. Be juſt.
<stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Parm.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>Is that the apartment of the <hi>Thracian</hi> Prince?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>Yes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>Or my Eyes deceive me, or I ſaw</l>
               <l>A woman enter there.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>You did, my Lord.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>By whoſe command?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>The Emp'rors, ſhe produc'd</l>
               <l>His Signet.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis impoſſible!</l>
               <l>But now</l>
               <l>We parted, and ſince laſt I ſaw thee, none</l>
               <l>Have been allow'd to ſee him but my ſelf.</l>
               <l>Confuſion! he has cheated me, or thou</l>
               <l>Art by ſome idle tale abus'd, I'll know</l>
               <l>The meaning of this Riddle, and by whom</l>
               <l>Thy truth has been debauch'd.
<stage>Would Enter, &amp; is ſtopt.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>My Lord forbear.</l>
               <l>To you this liberty I muſt defend.</l>
               <l>The Imperial Licence reaches only her.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>Oh Inſolence! art thou too of their plots?</l>
               <l>Let me no more be call'd the Emp'rors friend</l>
               <l>If I forget this Injury.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>Yourſelf</l>
               <l>Permitted only ſuch to paſs as brought.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:96247:20"/>My Maſters Signet; ſhe was firſt, and I</l>
               <l>Have ſworn to ſee the Emp'rors word obey'd.</l>
               <l>If pray'rs or charms that would have melted Rocks,</l>
               <l>Cou'd have ſeduc'd me from my truſt. To theſe</l>
               <l>I ſooner had ſubmitted than to threats.</l>
               <l>She tempted every ſence to try my Faith,</l>
               <l>My Ears with Muſick, that might match the Spheres,</l>
               <l>My Eyes with ſmiles that wou'd have won on Prieſts,</l>
               <l>And forc'd a Hermit to forget his Vow.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>From whnce theſe racking thoughts? it cannot be</l>
               <l>I tremble yet, as if my fears were true;</l>
               <l>Amidſt their ſports a Virgin I beheld,</l>
               <l>Who ſeem'd the Goddeſs of their mirth, and ſuch</l>
               <l>Was ſhe, her Beauty and her Art conſpir'd</l>
               <l>Alike, to triumph o're Mankind.</l>
               <l>Hadſt thou ne're ſeen this Lady? I grow mad.</l>
               <l>'Tis all Extravagance.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>My Lord, I gaz'd</l>
               <l>So much, and with ſuch pleaſure, I began</l>
               <l>To think I might have ſeen her oft in <hi>Greece.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>Where?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>In <hi>Byzantium.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVith the Princeſs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parm.</speaker>
               <l>Ha!</l>
               <l>If thou cou'dſt, unconcern'd, imagin this,</l>
               <l>Tho reaſon is againſt me, what I feel</l>
               <l>Confirms my jealouſies, and thy report.</l>
               <l>Six years the Princeſs has been loſt, and Fame</l>
               <l>Not once has nam'd the place to which ſhe ſled.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Martian,</hi> the Captain of <hi>Arcadius</hi> Guards,</l>
               <l>Convey'd her; him I ſtill remember well.</l>
               <l>True — Theſe are wanderers, but they roſe from Flocks</l>
               <l>And Herds to govern men— Beſides, I ne're</l>
               <l>Have met <hi>Amintor</hi> till I came to <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Why, when the Emp'ror of the Eaſt deſcends</l>
               <l>To grace this Manſion with his preſence, why</l>
               <l>Muſt ſhe be ſick at this unlucky hour?</l>
               <l>Who owns it, and of whom we heard ſuch talk.</l>
               <l>Sure, any one but he I ſerve, had gueſt</l>
               <l>E're now. What Treaſure could ſupport this coſt,</l>
               <l>'Tis plain, this Lady <hi>Nicias</hi> is the ſame,</l>
               <l>For whom the Prince of <hi>Thrace</hi> remains in bonds,</l>
               <l>And in eternal bonds muſt ſoon be laid.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>My Lord, you've rais'd ſuſpicions in my breaſt,</l>
               <l>Which make me wonder we could err ſo long.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Phyl. <hi>croſſes the Stage as from</hi> Adraſtus.</stage>
            <sp>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:96247:20"/>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>Then I will ſee. Diſtraction! I am fixt,</l>
               <l>My Limbs forſake me; what is this but Love?</l>
               <l>And who is ſhe that awes me thus unſeen?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phylante!</hi> coming from my Rivals arms:</l>
               <l>Ye Furies, can I fancy this and live?</l>
               <l>Time flies on nimble Wings, and I muſt haſte,</l>
               <l>Thou know'ſt of what importance 'tis to me</l>
               <l>And thee, whoſe Fortune wholly lives on mine,</l>
               <l>That ſince we have <hi>Adraſtus</hi> in our power,</l>
               <l>We ne'er may be in his—And if at laſt</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arcadius</hi> knows the ſecret we ſuſpect,</l>
               <l>Let this ſecure us both, and all the ſpoils
<stage>Gives a Dagger.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Of <hi>Thrace</hi> in equal portions ſhall be ours.</l>
               <l>The Emp'ror ſhall believe he gave the blow</l>
               <l>Himſelf, and freed from him, ſuppoſe the worſt,</l>
               <l>The Princeſs with her pardon will be pleas'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>All but my being, to your gift Lowe,</l>
               <l>Convinc'd, that if <hi>Adraſtus</hi> ſcapes us now,</l>
               <l>Not only you, my Lord, but I muſt fall,</l>
               <l>Which beſt inſtructs me what to do.
<stage>Ent. Emp. &amp; Train.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parm.</speaker>
               <l>Enough—</l>
               <l>The Emp'ror; we from him muſt keep our doubts,</l>
               <l>For he with rapture would receive the news,</l>
               <l>And we ſhould act in vain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>What further is diſcover'd, is our Hoſt</l>
               <l>In league for our deſtruction with the Prince,</l>
               <l>Or holds he guilty Commerce with our Foes?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>You beſt can tell what Commerce, Sir, he holds</l>
               <l>Your tydings are of later date than mine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>You ſpeak in fables, has your Wiſdom found</l>
               <l>New plots, or are you weary of the old.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parm.</speaker>
               <l>Whom you approve, my Lord, at leaſt in me</l>
               <l>'Twere folly to condemn. Perhaps my zeal</l>
               <l>Already has tranſported me too far?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>Our danger is your ſport; what means this change?</l>
               <l>Have you betray'd me to commit a deed,</l>
               <l>Outrageous to the ſanctity of Crowns.</l>
               <l>And would you when you ſee your weakneſs, throw</l>
               <l>The ſhame on us. No more, I am not now</l>
               <l>Diſpos'd to play with what concerns our life</l>
               <l>Or honour.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>We have reaſon to believe.</l>
               <l>You think, my Lord, that you are ſafe in both.</l>
               <l>The Lady, who this minute left the Prince,</l>
               <l>Whoſe word cou'd paſs where mine was hear! like wind,</l>
               <l>She doubtleſs has convinc'd you you are ſafe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:96247:21"/>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>What Lady? Still you keep me on the Rack?</l>
               <l>Who's this that has uſurpt ſuch mighty power?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>The pow'r was yours, your Signet licenc'd all.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>My Signet? ſee 'tis here — Nor have I ſeen</l>
               <l>A humane Face but theſe ſince thine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>Your Guards</l>
               <l>Will tell you what has paſt of late. I ſaw</l>
               <l>A Woman enter, and the Signet ſhewn.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic. &amp; Guard s.</speaker>
               <l>My Lord, 'twas yours, your Signet.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>Treaſon all.</l>
               <l>I'll have you to the Wheel, your Tongues will then</l>
               <l>Speak Truth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>My Lord, their truth deſerves reward,</l>
               <l>And thoſe the torture who abus'd your name.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>Excuſe me, by thy Friendſhip 'tis I live</l>
               <l>They cou'd not ſteel it from me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>Not ſo ſoon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>This miſchief muſt be old, and form'd in <hi>Greece.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Signet wrought by yours to be produc'd</l>
               <l>On all extremities, their Plots ſhould want.</l>
               <l>I wou'd have enter'd, and have ſeen by whom</l>
               <l>This trick was manag'd, but your Guards were told,</l>
               <l>The Imperial Warrant reacht to none but her.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>All falſhood; <hi>Nicias,</hi> keep your charge ſecure,</l>
               <l>When ſafety is reſtor'd us with the day,</l>
               <l>We'll leave this place of horror, and inflict</l>
               <l>Thoſe pains at leiſure, which their crimes require.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Roman</hi> Senate ſhall the Traytors Judge.
<stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Eud.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Well, Sir, you ſeem to have affairs of haſte,</l>
               <l>Which claim immediate Audience: ſo have we.</l>
               <l>Who's this with out our leave, preſumes to wear</l>
               <l>The Seal of Empire, which alone is ours,</l>
               <l>And in our name to viſit him, whom theſe</l>
               <l>In ſtrict Confinement hold?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>My Lord,</l>
               <l>Deceit's a ſtranger to this place, but where</l>
               <l>Our buſineſs calls us, we wou'd think at leaſt</l>
               <l>This houſe was free, the reſt I owe to you.</l>
               <l>In peace I kept my Flocks before, and beg</l>
               <l>That I again may hold my Crook in peace.</l>
               <l>For if my hands a Soveraigns Scepter weild,</l>
               <l>My heare will long to have a Soveraigns Right.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>Princes you are, yet all depend on us,</l>
               <l>As we on Heaven depend, nor dare you claim</l>
               <l>A Soveraigns pow'r, where we are pleas'd to reign.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>Happy ye Swains! who on the Mountain live,</l>
               <l>Lords of your homely Cells, your Cells are yours,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:96247:21"/>And none diſputes your right to govern there.</l>
               <l>Oh had you left me to my ſelf, this Vale,</l>
               <l>The purchaſe of my labour, had been ſtill</l>
               <l>The bounds of my Ambition; but my Ear</l>
               <l>Charm'd with a Princes name, has taught my Soul</l>
               <l>To think indeed that I am here to reign.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>We are not now to ask you whence this wealth,</l>
               <l>The Fleeces muſt be fine which yield ſuch Gold,</l>
               <l>Not that of <hi>Colchos</hi> was a richer prize.</l>
               <l>A Gueſt ſhou'd only wonder, and as yours,</l>
               <l>All curious inquiſition we forbear;</l>
               <l>And while you're fluſht with infant Grandeur, leave</l>
               <l>Such queſtions to ſome other place, and hour,</l>
               <l>Tho you, who can proteſt againſt our ſway,</l>
               <l>And in our preſence tell us what we ought.</l>
               <l>Poſſeſt of theſe, and viſions of your right,</l>
               <l>May once grow dangerous, Sir, you riſe too faſt.</l>
               <l>This we can pardon, but provokt again,</l>
               <l>You may be ſent to murmur with your Friend.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>He is my Friend, which ſoon th'aſtoniſht world</l>
               <l>Shall ſee: nor wou'd he thus have us'd a wretch</l>
               <l>VVho ſu'd for Juſtice. I cou'd tell what name</l>
               <l>The men of antient <hi>Greece</hi> had giv'n to Kings,</l>
               <l>VVho to their Subjects wrongs wou'd thus reply.</l>
               <l>Go on — and liſten to your Minions Tales.</l>
               <l>Howe'er, remember you too late ſhall know,</l>
               <l>Whom you have wrong'd, and curſe their pois'nous tongues</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>This Minute then we'll know. Guards!</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Alcan.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>Off ye Slaves!</l>
               <l>For by the Majeſty that awes my arm,</l>
               <l>He dies that in my houſe inſults me firſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>The Shepherd rages, leave him, he'll grow cool,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome</hi> is a milder air, and good to cure</l>
               <l>Diſtempers, which like his have ſeiz'd the blood.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Ex.</hi> Arc. <hi>and Train,</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>Muſt we like Captives then be led to <hi>Rome?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVait on his Chariot-wheels in chains, like thoſe</l>
               <l>His Sword has conquer'd in the Field.</l>
               <l>This morning Sun beheld me on a Throne,</l>
               <l>And oft his beams reflected on my Brows,</l>
               <l>Have borrow'd luſtre from the Crown I wore.</l>
               <l>And muſt I like a purchas'd Slave, be linkt</l>
               <l>With him, whom Nature and Deſert have made</l>
               <l>My Friend, who ſuffers all, and dies for me?</l>
               <l>Muſt this inevitably be, and I</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:96247:22"/>Submit with patience? Curſt be him who wears</l>
               <l>The marks of Bondage when he might be free.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alcander,</hi> are our Friends prepar'd?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alc.</speaker>
               <l>They are.</l>
               <l>All arming for your reſcue, but in vain,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Roman</hi> Guard of every Paſs poſſeſt,</l>
               <l>Oppoſes all aſſiſtance from without,</l>
               <l>A while to enter 'twas deny'd to me;</l>
               <l>Hadn't their Captain known me well, I ſcarce</l>
               <l>My ſelf had been allow'd to bring this news.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>Who now will doubt to what this treatment tends,</l>
               <l>We have been flatter'd with fallacious ſmiles,</l>
               <l>Till things were ready for our ſolemn fall.</l>
               <l>Why asks he not for her, whoſe crime his wrath</l>
               <l>Once ſwore he neither wou'd forgive in her,</l>
               <l>Nor in her memory; does his heart relent,</l>
               <l>And are we only deſtin'd to Revenge.</l>
               <l>So well I love <hi>Aurelia,</hi> I wou'd yield</l>
               <l>My ſelf a Sacrifice for her with joy.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Adraſtus</hi> — Why muſt he be puniſht firſt?</l>
               <l>'Tis doubtful all but this — My friend's in Bonds,</l>
               <l>And calls aloud for Liberty on me.</l>
               <l>Oh had he known I tamely cou'd behold</l>
               <l>My Brother bound and murder'd, how my ear</l>
               <l>This morn had ſuffer'd with his juſt reproach.</l>
               <l>One way is left us ſtill, if that ſhou'd fail,</l>
               <l>We'll charge the <hi>Roman</hi> Guard, and dye like men,</l>
               <l>Tho Conqueſt oft has waited on Deſpair.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alcander</hi>—let <hi>Dametas</hi> with his Band</l>
               <l>Be ready, and aſſoon's the alarm is heard</l>
               <l>Attack their Troop without, while I within</l>
               <l>Thro all that dare oppoſe us force my way:</l>
               <l>The reſt we'll leave to fate. Howe're it ends,</l>
               <l>'Tis brave to fall like Princes, and like Friends.</l>
            </sp>
            <trailer>End of the Fourth Act.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="act">
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:96247:22"/>
            <head>ACT V:</head>
            <stage>The Palace.</stage>
            <stage>Scene an Apartment near the Emperor's.</stage>
            <stage>Parmenio <hi>ſolus.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>OH Guilt! Oh curſt Remorſe, the bane of reſt,</l>
               <l>Which ſwims above my faireſt hopes by day,</l>
               <l>And with black Viſions haunts my dreams by night.</l>
               <l>But what is guilt, or what remorſe to me?</l>
               <l>The Cowards terrour, and the Preachers hell.</l>
               <l>Words made to frighten fools, who dread the wheel:</l>
               <l>Conſcience ne're meddles with ſucceſsful crimes.</l>
               <l>The Conq'ror o're a thouſand Murders ſleeps,</l>
               <l>The Miſer ſteals with pleaſure to his wealth,</l>
               <l>Torn from the poor, and ſmiles with inward joy</l>
               <l>While he who wants thoſe riches, views his ſins</l>
               <l>With partial Eyes, and fancies then he feels</l>
               <l>The Fury's whip, when hunger only ſtings.
<stage>Enter an Officer:</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Offi.</speaker>
               <l>Our Maſter's danger will excuſe my haſte,</l>
               <l>The Province is in arms, the foremoſt Guards</l>
               <l>Diſcover by the light of flaming Spears,</l>
               <l>Ten thouſand men in martial order move,</l>
               <l>And tow'rds the Palace ſeem to bend their courſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>I thank thee fate, this minute then is mine,</l>
               <l>It ſmiles propitious on my great deſigns.</l>
               <l>Their folly will diſpoſe the world to think</l>
               <l>My Counſels juſt, and Heaven rewards my zeal.</l>
               <l>What ſtrength can you oppoſe to theirs?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Offi.</speaker>
               <l>At moſt</l>
               <l>Five hundred; but of theſe, the better half</l>
               <l>Are Friends and Neighbours, and require to know</l>
               <l>For whom they fight, and talk but ill of you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>No more—You ſpeak as if you lik't their talk.</l>
               <l>Your Maſter ſoon will have it in his pow'r</l>
               <l>To puniſh ſuch as queſtion his commands
<stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Eud.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>There are whoſe ears wou'd burn at ſuch reports,</l>
               <l>This Souldier here ſhall teach 'em to obey,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:96247:23"/>Correct their doubts, and lead 'em to the Foe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>The Prince of <hi>Thrace,</hi> my Lord, demands to ſee</l>
               <l>The Emp'ror, and has ſomething to impart</l>
               <l>Of high concern.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>No, <hi>Nicias,</hi> 'tis in vain,</l>
               <l>The Emperor ſleeps, and muſt not be diſturb'd.</l>
               <l>Had he confeſt when favour took his part,</l>
               <l>His and his Friends diſhonour had been ſav'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Amyntor</hi>'s Subjects are, it ſeems, in arms,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Roman</hi> Guard in mutiny, and thou</l>
               <l>Canſt only bring 'em to obedience Both.</l>
               <l>Go Leave the <hi>Thracian</hi> Prince to me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>Knows not the Emp'ror of this ſtrange revolt?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>Scarce if he did, would he believe it true,</l>
               <l>His mercy finds excuſes for his Foes.</l>
               <l>Oft, in his changing humour, he reſolv'd,</l>
               <l>To free <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> and perhaps my ſelf</l>
               <l>Had for my care been ſent to wear his bonds.</l>
               <l>Oh horror! that ſuch goodneſs ſhou'd be wrong'd,</l>
               <l>By thoſe his bounty had ſo lately rais'd.</l>
               <l>That in theſe ſhades, where virtue ſeems to dwell,</l>
               <l>The Vice of Fiends, Ingratitude, ſhould reign.</l>
               <l>Go, <hi>Nicias,</hi> and be early in the War,</l>
               <l>Nor ſtay their Charge, the Rebels may diſperſe.</l>
               <l>And then we loſe our moment of revenge.</l>
               <l>Fall on the rout, the victory's ſecure,</l>
               <l>Scarce worthy of thy Sword; but know that much</l>
               <l>Depends on this, and great is thy reward.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>I fly where moſt my Maſters ſafety calls,</l>
               <l>And by the Empires Guardian Angel ſwear,</l>
               <l>The Traitors ſhall not ſcape, tho near the Throne.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Ex.</hi> Nic. <hi>and Officer.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>I like not that, this man was always brave,</l>
               <l>But honeſt always, and has known too much.</l>
               <l>No matter—He's remov'd, and now if Hell</l>
               <l>To glorious miſchief ever was a Friend,</l>
               <l>Too morrow's Sun ſhall ſee me firſt in pow'r,</l>
               <l>And firſt in bliſs of all the race of man.
<stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Eud.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>What brings <hi>Amintor</hi> here? my Genius ſtarts,</l>
               <l>Whene're we meet, his preſence bodes me ill.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>I've buſineſs with the Emp'ror.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>You're too late.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis of importance to his Life and Fame.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>To you, we know his Life and Fame are dear,</l>
               <l>You might have told him when you ſaw him laſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>Twas with a perſon I deſpiſe, and thought</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:96247:23"/>Unworthy of the ſecret.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>Him you mean</l>
               <l>Has Slaves, who ſcorn a Traytors odious name,</l>
               <l>And of your ſecrets is too well inform'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>Ha! Have a care how thou inſultſt me here.</l>
               <l>Thou know'ſt thy Fate is in the Secret lodg'd.</l>
               <l>Be wiſe. My patience will not ſuffer long.</l>
               <l>Tempt me no more. Behold me yet at large,</l>
               <l>Lord of this place, and Soveraign here.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>You talk indeed as if the World was yours:</l>
               <l>But men are ever fond of what is new.</l>
               <l>A Scepter looks but awkard in your hands,</l>
               <l>So lately ſully'd with a Crook. This Houſe</l>
               <l>Is yours, and this diſcourſe becomes it well.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>I have no leiſure to diſpute, I came</l>
               <l>To ſee <hi>Arcadius.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>I ne're ask'd for what.</l>
               <l>You might have ſpar'd this viſit; 'tis a time</l>
               <l>For reſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>I ſhall not ſee him?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>No. Hoa, Guards.
<stage>Enter Guards.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Thro theſe and me you firſt ſhall force your way.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>By heav'n thou durſt not truſt his ears with truth!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>I durſt not truſt him with the man whoſe Slaves,</l>
               <l>A numerous Hoſt, declare againſt his life.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>Thoſe Slaves ſhall quickly tear him from thy arms:</l>
               <l>Of thee the miſchiefs of this hour are born,</l>
               <l>And thou ſeverely ſhalt account for all.
<stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Alcander.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>Convince the Senate whence theſe miſchiefs roſe.</l>
               <l>Hence! to your poſt, and watch with double care.
<stage>To the Guards</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Nor fear their numbers in ſo juſt a cauſe.</l>
               <l>Nations and Kings will in our quarrel riſe,</l>
               <l>They've nothing to aſſiſt 'em but Deſpair.
<stage>Exit with Guards.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>That portion e're the morning ſhall be thine:</l>
               <l>Hell ne're receiv'd a blacker Soul, nor Earth</l>
               <l>A more malicious Villain ever bred.</l>
               <l>Night waſtes apace, and e're the day returns,</l>
               <l>There muſt be mighty changes in our Fates,</l>
               <l>For he or I no more ſhall ſee it dawn.</l>
               <l>What of <hi>Dametas,</hi> ſpeaks <hi>Parmenio</hi> true?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ale.</speaker>
               <l>I left him in the Vale, ten thouſand ſtrong,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lycon</hi> attends you in the Citron Grove,</l>
               <l>With fifty choſen youth: The foe without</l>
               <l>Forget, or never knew that paſs; within</l>
               <l>But five are poſted at the Gate, and thoſe</l>
               <l>We ſoon ſhall maſter, and with <hi>Lycon</hi> joyn.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:96247:24"/>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>Thy nows tranſports me, haſte, ſecure the Guards,</l>
               <l>Be careful of their Lives, receive our Friends,</l>
               <l>Bar all the Palace Gates, and leave at each</l>
               <l>Sufficient ſtrength, with charge to ſuffer none</l>
               <l>To enter or to paſs, let <hi>Lycon</hi> know</l>
               <l>I wait his entrance in the Inner Court.
<stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Alcander.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>I'll meet the Emp'ror like an Emp'rors Son;</l>
               <l>Nor on his Pity, or his Daughters Tears,</l>
               <l>Depend for pardon when I moſt am wrong'd.</l>
               <l>Oh, my <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> thou ſhalt ſee I ſtill</l>
               <l>Am worthy of the Heroes of our race.</l>
               <l>I fly to bring thee Freedom.</l>
               <l>Ha, my Wife!
<stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Aur. Phyl. Sylvia.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Am I unwelcome to my Lord? Not thus</l>
               <l>He wou'd have met me when our Loves were young.</l>
               <l>Why ſits ſuch thoughtful ſorrow on thy brow?</l>
               <l>My eyes were wont to kindle joy in thine.</l>
               <l>Am I the cauſe of theſe diſtracting cares?</l>
               <l>Am I more happy that my heart can find</l>
               <l>Relief in Love, and only think of thee?</l>
               <l>Have you not ſeen my Father?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>No, nor you.</l>
               <l>Nor muſt I ſee him, till <hi>Parmenio</hi>'s pleas'd.</l>
               <l>So far I preſt it, that the Guards were call'd</l>
               <l>To ſtop my paſſage — Where are now your hopes?</l>
               <l>The Traytor proudly told me 'twas too late,</l>
               <l>And bad me prove my innocence in <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dametas</hi> with an Army is at hand,</l>
               <l>I will be heard, and will have Juſtice done.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dametas</hi> is at hand, you will be heard,</l>
               <l>This ſtile with thirty Legions would agree,</l>
               <l>We dream of dangers which our fears create;</l>
               <l>And reaſon yielding to thoſe fears, the ills</l>
               <l>At laſt prove real that our fancies form'd</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>Blame not a paſſion, which I learnt with love,</l>
               <l>Fear was till then a ſtranger to my Soul.</l>
               <l>I thought of loſing you, and then I fear'd.</l>
               <l>Twas then I trembled firſt, forgot my Sex,</l>
               <l>And felt a woman's ſoftneſs in my heart.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Oh wou'd that ſoftneſs argue with me now,</l>
               <l>For ever you muſt loſe me, if you go.</l>
               <l>Againſt you <hi>Greece</hi> will ſend forth all her pow'rs,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Rome,</hi> her Siſter, turn her force on you.</l>
               <l>Where will your Army ſly for refuge then?</l>
               <l>Their Flocks and Herds, their Virgins and their Wives,</l>
               <l>Their Woods, their Groves, will be the Soldiers ſpoil,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:96247:24"/>And this fair Land of pleaſure then lye waſte,</l>
               <l>While I abandon'd to my Father's rage,</l>
               <l>Expos'd to Death, or what is worſe, am left,</l>
               <l>By all unpity'd, and by all forſook.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>Say, wou'd you have me led in chains to <hi>Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shown for a Monſter to the gaping crowd,</l>
               <l>And with my Brother, on a Scaffold fall</l>
               <l>The Victim of a jealous Minions luſt?</l>
               <l>The Emp'ror leaves us with the Riſing day,</l>
               <l>My Foe is conſcious of his guilt, and far</l>
               <l>Will keep me from his Maſter's Ear, till <hi>Rome</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Has ſeen my ſhame, and we can ne're be friends.</l>
               <l>Oh no, <hi>Aurelia,</hi> things muſt ne're be thus,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Adraſtus</hi> muſt be ſafe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arcadius</hi> undeceiv'd.</l>
               <l>His honour's equally concern'd with mine,</l>
               <l>Both by a perjur'd Villain are abus'd,</l>
               <l>And by this Sword we will have juſtice both.</l>
               <l>Farewel — To pleaſe thee wou'd be ruin,</l>
               <l>But not to pleaſe thee I muſt hear no more.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Stay, my <hi>Eudoſius,</hi> ſtay, he's gone, he's gone</l>
               <l>To certain Death, nor gave a parting kiſs,</l>
               <l>Nor cloſe embrace, but tore him from my arms,</l>
               <l>My longing arms, that ne're muſt claſp him more.</l>
               <l>What, am I grown a burden to his Heart,</l>
               <l>Have I for this endur'd a Parents curſe?</l>
               <l>For this the Kingdoms of the world refus'd,</l>
               <l>For this to Menial Offices comply'd,</l>
               <l>And been as much his Servant as his Wife.</l>
               <l>Oh man, oh falſe ungrateful man! Oh thou</l>
               <l>Of all thy Sex moſt falſe, and moſt ingrate,</l>
               <l>Where haſt thou left me? but no matter where,</l>
               <l>Since to be left for ever is a fate,</l>
               <l>No circumſtance of Woe can render worſe.</l>
               <l>My Father ſoon will ſeek me in his wrath,</l>
               <l>And when his hard reproaches wound my ear,</l>
               <l>Hadſt thou been near me to relieve my ſhame,</l>
               <l>And in thy boſom hide me from his frown,</l>
               <l>His awful Brow had ſhot its darts in vain.</l>
               <l>But now, thus deſtitute of help from thee,</l>
               <l>My crimes appear ſo black, my Judge ſo fierce,</l>
               <l>I dye with terrour, e're my doom is read.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <l>When by our griefs, our reaſon is oppreſt,</l>
               <l>How weak are all our arguments, how vain,</l>
               <l>Has he not ſuffer'd equally with you,</l>
               <l>And I who have no intereſt but yours,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:96247:25"/>Have not I had my ſhare, and yet ev'n now,</l>
               <l>When moſt I ſuffer, I repent it leaſt:</l>
               <l>Was nothing to his Brothers Injuries due,</l>
               <l>Muſt poor <hi>Adraſtus</hi> ſtill remain in chains,</l>
               <l>Or for his freedom wait his Rivals Nod?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Too morrow I had paſt thro Swords and Spears,</l>
               <l>Thro pointed Deaths, and at my Fathers feet</l>
               <l>Implor'd his pity, clung about his knees,</l>
               <l>And of my Mothers beauteous Image full,</l>
               <l>Hung on his neck, and bath'd it with my tears,</l>
               <l>Till to our wiſh I had inclin'd his Soul.</l>
               <l>But oh my Husbands uſeleſs Fury adds</l>
               <l>New Fuel to his Flame, when Peace was nigh.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <l>Ceaſe, ceaſe, theſe mournings, all things will be well.</l>
               <l>The War is with <hi>Parmenio,</hi> not his Lord.</l>
               <l>The Emp'ror will himſelf applaud his Son,</l>
               <l>And when he ſees his Favorite's curſt deſigns,</l>
               <l>Throw him with horrour from his arms.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <stage>(within)</stage>
Oh my <hi>Philante!</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <l>Heard you not a voice?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>I did, it nam'd you, and the ſound came thence.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <l>Th'apartment where <hi>Adraſtus</hi> is confin'd.</l>
               <l>Sure 'twas his Genius, or my own, that call'd,</l>
               <l>To warn me of our danger. Oh my heart!</l>
               <l>Why ſinks it in my breaſt, why ſhake my limbs?</l>
               <l>Why theſe ill Bodings, if my Prince is ſafe?</l>
               <l>Oh no, I ſee the bloody hand advanc'd,</l>
               <l>The Dagger lifted high, his heart its aim.</l>
               <l>Stop, ſtop, inhuman Butcher, ſtrike it here,</l>
               <l>The wound is mine, my Breaſt ſhall be his Shield.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sylv.</speaker>
               <l>How well we counſel others, and how ill,</l>
               <l>When our greifs diſturb us, act our ſelves?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Where e're we turn, we meet with new diſtreſs.</l>
               <l>New Scenes of woe, new Images of death.</l>
               <l>Fly, <hi>Sylvia,</hi> from this moſt unhappy wretch,</l>
               <l>This out-caſt, this forſaken woman, fly,</l>
               <l>My Friendſhip ruins what it holds moſt dear.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
               <l>Madam, Retire, you're here too much exposd:</l>
               <l>Rous'd by the noiſe and perils of the night,</l>
               <l>The Emp'ror arm'd with Thunder will appear,</l>
               <l>And if he ſees you in the firſt alarm,</l>
               <l>How fatal may the meeting be to both.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Yes! here this <hi>Jove,</hi> this Thund'rer I'll expect,</l>
               <l>I'll ſtand between my Lord and him, and bear</l>
               <l>The dreadful weight of his reſentment here.</l>
               <l>On me the Tempeſt firſt ſhall break, on me</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:96247:25"/>The edge of his inſufferable rage</l>
               <l>Shall fall, till thus it ſtrikes me to the Earth.
<stage>falls.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Thus low I'll bleſs him with my lateſt ſighs,</l>
               <l>And pray that his revenge may end with me.
<stage>
                     <hi>Enter Emp. and</hi> Nic.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sylv.</speaker>
               <l>Oh ſave us, ye immortal powers, he comes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>Is he not dead?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>No.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>Bring him forth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>My Lord!</l>
               <l>The poiſon's in his brain, his Fancies rove</l>
               <l>On things extravagant, the Fever paſt,</l>
               <l>He may e're death be ſenſible and calm.</l>
               <l>What dropt from him before was only this,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Parmenio</hi> left the Criſtal Bowl with him,</l>
               <l>Commanding when you call'd to give it you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Parmenio?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>Yes, <hi>Parmenio.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>Have a care,</l>
               <l>To name him thus is death,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>I'll mark the man.</l>
               <l>Then call him what you pleaſe, my Lord, 'twas he</l>
               <l>That from a Soldier rais'd me to command:</l>
               <l>To this high poſt, and plac'd me near the Throne.</l>
               <l>'Twas he, that from as vile Conditions roſe,</l>
               <l>By <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s favour next to <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s rank.</l>
               <l>'Twas he that counſell'd you to break the league,</l>
               <l>And ſeize <hi>Adraſtus</hi> in profoundeſt peace.</l>
               <l>'Twas he that charg'd me when the truth was known,</l>
               <l>To fix this Dagger in his Rival's heart,</l>
               <l>Then ſwear to you he gave the blow himſelf.</l>
               <l>'Twas he that bid me lead your Guards, and waſte</l>
               <l>This Land with unexpected War. 'Twas he</l>
               <l>That left you to the ſervice of his Slaves:</l>
               <l>For I in diſobedience to his will,</l>
               <l>Unknown to him within the Palace ſtay'd,</l>
               <l>To watch your ſleep, which elſe had been your laſt.</l>
               <l>When Hell and darkneſs tempted him abroad,</l>
               <l>To execute the Treaſons he had form'd.</l>
               <l>'Twas he, that when <hi>Amintor</hi> would have ſhewn,</l>
               <l>How foul, how falſe, the charge againſt him was,</l>
               <l>Withſtood his entrance, and by open force</l>
               <l>Compell'd the Prince by force to make his way.</l>
               <l>But oh! Great Emp'ror, what need I more,</l>
               <l>'Twas he by whom that high-born Princeſs dies,</l>
               <l>In whoſe freſh youth divine <hi>Pulcheria</hi> lives.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sylv.</speaker>
               <l>Help! help! the Princeſs faints.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:96247:26"/>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>Oh Heav'n! oh Joy!
<stage>Swoons</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Tis ſhe, I know 'tis ſhe, I feel her here,</l>
               <l>Nature ſpeaks loud, and points me to my Child.</l>
               <l>Oh Daughter! oh <hi>Aurelia!</hi> oh my Tongue</l>
               <l>Is loſt with rapture, but with this, and this,
<stage>Embrace.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Once more I'll give thee life — ſhe lives, ſhe lives,</l>
               <l>Thus lookt <hi>Pulcheria</hi> when ſhe lookt her laſt,</l>
               <l>That dying glance reſtores her to my Heart,</l>
               <l>Which weaken'd with exceſs of joy, grows ſick.
<stage>Faints.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>My Lord, my Emp'ror!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Where am I? Is not this the Land of Peace,</l>
               <l>Where all things are forgiv'n, all are bleſt,</l>
               <l>Did not my Father call me Child?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
               <l>He did.</l>
               <l>Behold him in your arms with tranſport loſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Oh Father, Father.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>Art thou then awake?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Forgive my heart, 'tis yet ſo buſie, Sir,</l>
               <l>My ſins are baniſht thence, and I can ſpare</l>
               <l>No time to beg your pardon.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>Name no more</l>
               <l>What I ſhou'd ask, for all that's paſt was mine;</l>
               <l>I ſpeak not of thy Husband, he's my friend,</l>
               <l>A thouſand things to my remembrance bring</l>
               <l>Both him and thee: The Signet, this retreat,</l>
               <l>The flying rumours that <hi>Eudoſius</hi> liv'd,</l>
               <l>His Brothers Friendſhip, and the Princes Love.</l>
               <l>Confirm theſe wonders.</l>
               <l>Go <hi>Nicias,</hi> go my Souldier, ſeek my Son,</l>
               <l>Go tell him how my arms are fill'd, and ſay</l>
               <l>While they want him I think 'em empty ſtill.
<stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Nic.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Oh had we met before! But then, my Child.</l>
               <l>The great diſcovery we have made to night</l>
               <l>Had ſtill been diſtant, and <hi>Parmenio</hi> lov'd.</l>
               <l>I bred and nurſt a Serpent in my breaſt,</l>
               <l>Whoſe venom'd ſting againſt my life was aim'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>We knew you wou'd not always hate us, Sir;</l>
               <l>Nor drive your Children from you, and e're morn</l>
               <l>Had told the ſecret with a kind ſurprize,</l>
               <l>Had not his jealouſie contriv'd theſe ills,</l>
               <l>And fill'd this houſe with ſorrow and deſpair.
<stage>Enter Officer.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Offic.</speaker>
               <l>My Lord, I waited on <hi>Parmenio</hi>'s Slave,</l>
               <l>Catcht his laſt words, and thus he dying ſaid,</l>
               <l>My Maſter put the Potion in the Cup,</l>
               <l>I, curious of its richneſs, taſted, drank,</l>
               <l>Fell down, when <hi>Nicias</hi> entring broke the Bowl.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:96247:26"/>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>See that he ſcapes not: Bear him to the Rack.</l>
               <l>I cou'd almoſt forgive him his offence
<stage>Ex. Offic.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>To me: But what he meant my Children rhrows</l>
               <l>Him far from mercy.</l>
               <stage>
                  <hi>A Shout. Enter</hi> Eudoſius, <hi>throws down his Sword, and kneels at the Emperors feet.</hi>
               </stage>
               <l>Oh my Son.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>My Emp'ror, my Father, can you hear</l>
               <l>That word from me, and ſtill preſerve your ſmile?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>Oh talk of nothing but of bliſs to come,</l>
               <l>Let dark oblivion bury what is paſt,</l>
               <l>And perfect as our bleſſing be our joy,</l>
               <l>The world has nam'd your Vertues with applauſe,</l>
               <l>More to your merit than your birth you owe.</l>
               <l>Take, take your Wife, and be for ever bleſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>Oh my <hi>Aurelia!</hi> have we liv'd to ſee</l>
               <l>This hour, and muſt we live another ſtill.</l>
               <l>Forgive me, Sir, all Extaſy is rude;</l>
               <l>'Tis new, we ne're cou'd thus embrace before,</l>
               <l>Nor hope a bleſſing on the Nuptial Bed.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <stage>within.</stage>
Bear down the Doors, the Pillars and the Walls,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Oh 'tis <hi>Phylante</hi>'s voice.
<stage>A Woman ſhrieks.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>The kind companion of your youth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>Tis her's,</l>
               <l>The Traytor loves her, and I dread his luſt.
<stage>Shriek.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Within.</speaker>
               <l>Help, help, the Prince, <hi>Phylante.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>Ha, I'm wing'd</l>
               <l>To reſcue thee, and pray it be'nt too late.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>How near deſtruction have I blindly walkt.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phylante,</hi> oh my Siſter.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <stage>within.</stage>
Seize on the Traytor, and unbind the Prince,</l>
               <l>Throw wide the doors, and let the Fiend be ſeen.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Scene opens,</hi> Adraſtus <hi>appears (unbinding)</hi> Phlyante <hi>in diſorder,</hi> Parmenio <hi>(held by Soldiers) disfigur'd as by a woman,</hi> Nicias, <hi>Officer and all come forward.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>My Brother!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Adr.</speaker>
               <l>My Deliverer!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phyl.</speaker>
               <l>My Preſerver!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>See,</l>
               <l>Your Duty to the Emp'ror firſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>Come to my arms, if you can think that one</l>
               <l>Who much has wrong'd you, can deſerve your love,</l>
               <l>And thou, my other Daughter, welcome here.</l>
               <l>To Torture with that Villain, Whips and Death,</l>
               <l>Slow lazy Deaths, away—
<stage>
                     <hi>Guards carry off</hi> Par.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:96247:27"/>
               <speaker>Phyl.</speaker>
               <l>Words are not black enough to paint his Crimes.</l>
               <l>When in this place we parted laſt, I went
<stage>
                     <hi>To</hi> Aur<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </stage>
               </l>
               <l>And found, alas! the Voice I heard was his.</l>
               <l>He ſeiz'd me, caught me to his arms, and ſaid,</l>
               <l>He knew me when I viſited the Prince.</l>
               <l>He told me if I'd yield to be his Wife,</l>
               <l>The morn ſhould find me Miſtreſs of the world:</l>
               <l>For, as he ſwore, the Emp'ror was no more.</l>
               <l>If not, he wou'd by force enjoy his wiſh,</l>
               <l>When for my honour, and the Princes life,
<stage>
                     <hi>To</hi> Eud.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Your timely ſuccour came.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>No tears, <hi>Phylante!</hi> now, no ſighs but ſuch</l>
               <l>As Lovers when th' expected minute comes</l>
               <l>Can ſpare. To you, <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> I am ſure,</l>
               <l>This preſent will be welcome. Take her, Prince,</l>
               <l>Our ſelf will witneſs to your Nuptial Vows;</l>
               <l>Thou, <hi>Nicias,</hi> to whoſe Loyalty we owe</l>
               <l>Life, Children, Empire, all, thou next to theſe</l>
               <l>In favour and in Friendſhip ſhalt be firſt.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thrace</hi> ſhall again behold her darling Lord,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Crown ſhall hence be regal, and the bounds</l>
               <l>Of this fair Province, which I gave my Son,</l>
               <l>Far as the <hi>Adriatick</hi> ſhall extend.</l>
               <l>This to <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> with his Bride I give.</l>
               <l>Renew the ſports theſe tumults have diſturb'd,</l>
               <l>With double Luſtre gild the face of night,</l>
               <l>That day approaching, may with wonder ſee</l>
               <l>Alight Superiour to his own.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Eud.</hi> &amp; <hi>Aur.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Hear us, Oh Father! grant our laſt requeſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <stage>(kneeling.)</stage>
Suffer no limits to your goodneſs, long</l>
               <l>This Garden has been ours, and ſweet its walks;</l>
               <l>To leave theſe Shades, and launch into the world,</l>
               <l>Looks frightful to our Natures, fond of reſt.</l>
               <l>Oh let <hi>Adraſtus</hi> wear the Crown of <hi>Thrace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This people and this Valley only ours,</l>
               <l>Where hand in hand, we may frequent its Groves,</l>
               <l>Talk of paſt changes, and rejoice in this.</l>
               <l>There with the morning and the Evening Sun,</l>
               <l>With pray'rs for you and <hi>Greece</hi> we'll viſit Heav'n.</l>
               <l>Nor will we here be negligent of fame;</l>
               <l>For Love and Glory ſhall divide our care.</l>
               <l>And thus like perſons who have reacht the ſhoar,</l>
               <l>With pleaſure we'll look back upon the Waves,</l>
               <l>And hear the Billows roar, and ſee 'em foam,</l>
               <l>While we ſecurely tread the ſolid Main.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:96247:27"/>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <l>Of this hereafter we'll reſolve.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eud.</speaker>
               <l>And now</l>
               <l>Let all our Military Train diſperſe,</l>
               <l>Let only thoſe who wait upon our ſports</l>
               <l>Attend, let Love and Mirth ſucceed our Cares,</l>
               <l>And Arms and Battles yield to ſofter Wars.</l>
            </sp>
            <trailer>End of the Fifth Act.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <stage>Scene the Temple of Love.</stage>
            <stage>
               <hi>Cupid</hi> is ſeen lying in his Mothers Lap.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cupid.</speaker>
               <l>APpear, old <hi>Hymen,</hi> from thy Cell,</l>
               <l>Where unſpotted Pleaſures dwell;</l>
               <l>Where thy Torch with Beauteous light</l>
               <l>Triumphs o're the ſhades of night.</l>
               <l>Come, at <hi>Cupid</hi>'s dread command,</l>
               <l>Joyn theſe happy Lovers hand:</l>
               <l>Let 'em be for ever joyn'd,</l>
               <l>He be conſtant, ſhe be kind.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Brisk Muſick, while</hi> Hymen <hi>comes forward.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hymen.</speaker>
               <l>Love they ſay is my God, tho to tell you the truth,</l>
               <l>I think he's at beſt but a ſlippery youth.</l>
               <l>He bids me come to you, ye wonder I came</l>
               <l>No ſooner; why as I grow old I grow lame;</l>
               <l>By which it falls out, as mayhap it does here,</l>
               <l>I oft come a day or two after the Fair.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prieſt of Love.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hymen</hi> joyns you, happy pair,</l>
               <l>Taſte the ſweets of harmleſs pleaſure.</l>
               <l>Joys which you v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no need to fear,</l>
               <l>Without guilt and without meaſure.</l>
               <l>Love has bleſt thee happy Swain,</l>
               <l>Go poſſeſs his richeſt T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>re,</l>
               <l>Happy Maid you bluſh in vain,</l>
               <l>Duty now is joyn d with Pleaſure.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Three Pr. of Love<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </speaker>
               <l>To Love we'll laſting homage pay</l>
               <l>For the high bleſſings of this day;</l>
               <l>New Altars to his name we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> raiſe,</l>
               <l>And ev ry Tongue ſhall ſpeak his praiſe,</l>
               <l>And ev'ry Heart his pow r adore,</l>
               <l>For none ean hurt or bleſs us more.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:96247:28"/>
               <speaker>Votary.</speaker>
               <l>The Hero his Lawrels to Love ſhall reſign,</l>
               <l>The Courtier his Pride, and the Toper his Wine;</l>
               <l>The Saint his Devotion, the Virgin her Vow,</l>
               <l>All ſtates and conditions, the high and the low.</l>
               <l>All Ages and Sexes to <hi>Cupid</hi> ſhall bow.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
               <l>The Saint his Devotion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grand Chorus.</speaker>
               <l>Raiſe you Notes, and lift 'em high,</l>
               <l>Love's Immortal Praiſes ſing,</l>
               <l>O're the Valley let 'em ring,</l>
               <l>For Muſick charms the pow'rs above amidſt their mighty joy.</l>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:96247:28"/>
            <head>EPILOGUE.</head>
            <byline>Writ by Mr <hi>Farquhar.</hi>
            </byline>
            <l>TIme was when Poets rul'd without diſputes,</l>
            <l>Turn'd Men to Gods, transform'd their Gods to Brutes.</l>
            <l>Our Poets change the Scene, with mighty odds</l>
            <l>Make Men the Brutes, make nothing of their Gods.</l>
            <l>'Tis ſtrange to ſee by what ſurprizing skill,</l>
            <l>Things are transforme'd by Brothers of the Quill.</l>
            <l>No more than this — high — <hi>Preſto</hi>—paſs,</l>
            <l>Great <hi>Jupiter</hi>'s a Bull—Great Beaux's an Aſs.</l>
            <l>Whene' er they pleaſe to give their thoughts a looſe,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Jove</hi>'s made a Swan, your Alderman's a Gooſe.</l>
            <l>Things of moſt differing forms too we may find,</l>
            <l>By ſpells of Poetry in one combin'd.</l>
            <l>The bluſtering Face, which Red-Coats bear about,</l>
            <l>Is the falſe Flag which Cowards ſtill hang out,</l>
            <l>And that ſhall huff, and rant, ſwear loud and ban,</l>
            <l>Hector his God, and yet be kickt by Man.</l>
            <l>They make the Villain look preciſe and grave,</l>
            <l>And the poor harmleſs Cit, a thriving Knave.</l>
            <l>Strange contradictions! reconcil'd we ſee,</l>
            <l>They ſometimes make even Man and Wife agree.</l>
            <l>Poets of Old chang'd <hi>Io</hi> to a Cow,</l>
            <l>But what ſtrange Monſters Women are made now?</l>
            <l>Females with us, without the Poet's fraud,</l>
            <l>Change often to the worſt of Beaſts, a Bawd.</l>
            <l>There are but two things from all change ſecure,</l>
            <l>Nought can transform a Poet or a Whore.</l>
            <l>Others for being chang'd, their Stars may blame,</l>
            <l>Their puniſhment is this—ſtill they're the ſame,</l>
            <l>Like paint on Glaſs that's valu'd at ſuch coſt;</l>
            <l>Poets ne're fade, altho the Art be loſt.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:96247:29"/>
            <head>BOOKS printed for <hi>R. Parker,</hi> at the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn</hi> under the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="books" type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>CHarron</hi> of Wiſdom, 2 Vol. tranſlated by Dr <hi>Stanhope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Echards Roman</hi> Hiſtory, from the building of the City, to the removal of the Imperial Seat, by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, two Volumes.</p>
               <p>Revolutions in <hi>Sweden,</hi> occaſioned by the change of Religion, and alteration of the Government in that Kingdom. Written in <hi>French</hi> by the Abbot <hi>Vertot,</hi> tranſlated by Dr <hi>Mitchel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gennes</hi> Voyage to <hi>Africa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Modeſt Critick by <hi>Rapin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Poems on ſeveral occaſions, written in imitation of the manner of <hi>Anacreon,</hi> with other Poems, Letters, and Tranſlations. By Mr <hi>Oldmixon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Gentlemans Journal, or Monthly Miſcellany. By Mr <hi>Motteux,</hi> either whole ſets or ſingle ones.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Busby</hi>'s <hi>Greek</hi> Grammer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cambridge</hi> Phraſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sydenham</hi>'s compleat method of curing almoſt all Diſeaſes, and deſcription of their Symptoms, with an abridgment of 5 diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of the ſame Author, <hi>viz.</hi> The Pleuriſy, Gout, Hyſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Paſſion, Dropſy, and Rheumatiſm.</p>
               <p>Art of preſerving and reſtoring health, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beraults Latin</hi> Grammer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Vocabulary of all the Verbs in the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue, with their Preter Tenſes and Supines, with the caſe they govern in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, by <hi>A. Paterſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The uſefulneſs of the Stage to the happineſs of Mankind, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Religion, occaſioned by Mr <hi>Collier</hi>'s view of the Stage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By Mr <hi>Dennis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An Account of a Voyage from <hi>Archangel</hi> in <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> in the year 1697.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="plays" type="part">
               <head>PLAYS.</head>
               <p>Plot and no Plot, a Comedy by Mr <hi>Dennis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Novelty, every Act a Play, by Mr <hi>Motteux.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beauty in diſtreſs, a Tragedy, by Mr <hi>Motteux.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> a Tragedy by Mr <hi>Dennis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Unhappy Kindneſs, or the fruitleſs Revenge, a Tragedy, by Mr <hi>Scot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neglected Virtue, or the Unhappy Conquerer.</p>
               <p>Loves laſt ſhift or the Fool in Faſhion by Mr <hi>Cibber</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amyntor</hi> a Paſtoral by Mr <hi>Oldmixon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
